<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
 <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
 <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
 <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]> 

<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-regext-rdap-geofeed-14" number="9877" updates="" obsoletes="" consensus="true" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true">

<front>
  <title abbrev="RDAP Geofeed">Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) Extension for Geofeed Data</title>
  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9877"/>
  <author initials="J." surname="Singh" fullname="Jasdip Singh">
    <organization>ARIN</organization>
    <address>
      <email>jasdips@arin.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author initials="T." surname="Harrison" fullname="Tom Harrison">
    <organization>APNIC</organization>
    <address>
      <email>tomh@apnic.net</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <date month="October" year="2025"/>
  <area>ART</area>
  <workgroup>regext</workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>This document defines a new Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) extension, &quot;geofeed1&quot;, for indicating that an RDAP
server hosts geofeed URLs for its IP network objects. It also defines a new media type and a new link relation type for
the associated link objects included in responses.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t><xref target="RFC8805"></xref> and <xref target="RFC9632"></xref> detail the IP geolocation feed (commonly known as 'geofeed') file format and associated
access mechanisms. While <xref target="RFC9632"></xref> describes how a registry can make geofeed URLs available by way of a Routing
Policy Specification Language (RPSL) <xref target="RFC2622"></xref> service, the Regional Internet Registries (RIRs) have deployed
Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) (<xref target="RFC7480"></xref>, <xref target="RFC7481"></xref>, <xref target="RFC9082"></xref>, <xref target="RFC9083"></xref>) services as successors to
RPSL for Internet number resource registrations, and maintaining feature parity between the two services supports client
transition from RPSL to RDAP in this context. To that end, this document specifies how geofeed URLs can be accessed
through RDAP. It defines a new RDAP extension, &quot;geofeed1&quot;, for indicating that an RDAP server hosts geofeed URLs for its
IP network objects, as well as a new media type and a new link relation type for the associated link objects.</t>
<t>Fetching and making use of geofeed data is out of scope for the purposes of this document. See <xref target="RFC8805"></xref> and
<xref target="RFC9632"></xref> for further details.</t>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>
<t>Indentation and whitespace in examples are provided only to illustrate element relationships and are not required
features of this specification.</t>
<t>&quot;...&quot; in examples is used as shorthand for elements defined outside of this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="specification"><name>Specification</name>

<section anchor="media_type_for_a_geofeed_link"><name>Media Type for a Geofeed Link</name>
<t><xref target="RFC9632"></xref> requires a geofeed file to be a UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"></xref> comma-separated values (CSV) file, with a series of &quot;#&quot;
comments at the end for the optional Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) <xref target="RFC6480"></xref> signature. At first glance,
the &quot;text/csv&quot; media type seems like a good candidate for a geofeed file, since it supports the &quot;#&quot; comments needed for
including the RPKI signature.</t>
<t>However, although the CSV geofeed data could be viewed directly by a user such that the &quot;text/csv&quot; media type was
appropriate, the most common use case will involve it being processed by some sort of application first, in order to
facilitate subsequent IP address lookup operations. Therefore, using a new &quot;application&quot; media type with a &quot;geofeed&quot;
subtype (<xref target="RFC6838" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.5"></xref>) for the geofeed data is preferable to using &quot;text/csv&quot;.</t>
<t>To that end, this document registers a new &quot;application/geofeed+csv&quot; media type in the IANA "Media Types" registry (see
<xref target="media_types_registry"></xref>), and a new &quot;+csv&quot; suffix in the IANA "Structured Syntax Suffixes" registry (see
<xref target="structured_syntax_suffixes_registry"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="geofeed_link"><name>Geofeed Link</name>
<t>An RDAP server that hosts geofeed URLs for its IP network objects (<xref target="RFC9083" sectionFormat="of" section="5.4"></xref>) may include link objects
for those geofeed URLs in IP network objects in its responses. These link objects are added to the &quot;links&quot; member of
each object (<xref target="RFC9083" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2"></xref>).</t>
<t>In RDAP, the &quot;value&quot;, &quot;rel&quot;, and &quot;href&quot; JSON members are required for any link object. Additionally, for a geofeed link
object, the &quot;type&quot; JSON member is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>. The geofeed-specific components of a link object are like so:</t>

<dl spacing="normal" newline="false">
  <dt>&quot;rel&quot;:</dt>
  <dd>The link relation type is set to &quot;geofeed&quot;. This is a new link
  relation type for IP geolocation feed data, registered in the IANA "Link
  Relations" registry (see <xref target="link_relations_registry"></xref>) by
  this document.</dd>
  <dt>&quot;href&quot;:</dt>
  <dd>The target URL is set to the HTTPS URL of the geofeed file (<xref
  target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="6"></xref>) for an IP
  network.</dd>
  <dt>&quot;type&quot;:</dt>
  <dd>&quot;application/geofeed+csv&quot; (see <xref target="media_type_for_a_geofeed_link"></xref>).</dd>
</dl>
<t>An IP network object returned by an RDAP server <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain zero or more geofeed link objects, though typically an IP
network will have either zero or only one. The scenario where more than one geofeed link object could be
returned is when the server is able to represent that data in multiple languages. In such a case, the server <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
provide &quot;hreflang&quot; members for the geofeed link objects. Except for the multiple-languages scenario, the server <bcp14>SHOULD
NOT</bcp14> return more than one geofeed link object.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="extension-identifier"><name>Extension Identifier</name>
<t>This document defines a new extension identifier, &quot;geofeed1&quot;, for use by servers that host geofeed URLs for their IP
network objects and include geofeed URL link objects in their responses to clients in accordance with <xref target="geofeed_link"></xref>. A
server that uses this extension identifier <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include it in the &quot;rdapConformance&quot; array (<xref target="RFC9083" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1"></xref>) for
any lookup or search response containing an IP network object, as well as in the help response. Here is an elided
example of this inclusion:</t>

<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "rdapConformance": [ "rdap_level_0", "geofeed1", ... ],
    ...
}]]></sourcecode>
<t>If the server includes &quot;geofeed1&quot; in the &quot;rdapConformance&quot; array, then for any response concerning a particular IP
network object for which the server possesses a geofeed URL and is able to return it to the client (i.e., the server is not
compelled to omit it due to regulatory constraints or similar), the server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a corresponding geofeed link
object in the response.</t>
<t>An RDAP server may make use of the &quot;application/geofeed+csv&quot; media type and the &quot;geofeed&quot; link relation defined in this
specification in its responses without including the &quot;geofeed1&quot; extension identifier in those responses, because RDAP
servers are free to use any registered media type or link relation in a standard response without implementing any
particular extension. The additional value of including the extension identifier in the &quot;rdapConformance&quot; array is that
it signals to the client that the server hosts geofeed URLs for its IP network objects. This is useful where a client
receives an IP network object without a geofeed link object, because in that case the client can infer that no geofeed
data is available for that object, since the server would have provided it if it were available.</t>
<t>Although a server may use registered media types in its link objects without any restrictions, it is useful to define
new RDAP extensions for those media types in order for the server to communicate to clients that it will make data for
that type accessible. This is what the server does with the &quot;geofeed1&quot; extension identifier.</t>
<t>The &quot;1&quot; in &quot;geofeed1&quot; denotes that this is version 1 of the geofeed extension.  New versions of the geofeed extension
will use different extension identifiers.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="example"><name>Example</name>
<t>The following is an elided example of an IP network object with a geofeed link object:</t>
<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[{
    "objectClassName": "ip network",
    "handle": "XXXX-RIR",
    "startAddress": "2001:db8::",
    "endAddress": "2001:db8:0:ffff:ffff:ffff:ffff:ffff",
    "ipVersion": "v6",
    "name": "NET-RTR-1",
    "type": "DIRECT ALLOCATION",
    "country": "AU",
    "parentHandle": "YYYY-RIR",
    "status": [ "active" ],
    "links":
     [
        {
            "value": "https://example.net/ip/2001:db8::/48",
            "rel": "self",
            "href": "https://example.net/ip/2001:db8::/48",
            "type": "application/rdap+json"
        },
        {
            "value": "https://example.net/ip/2001:db8::/48",
            "rel": "geofeed",
            "href": "https://example.com/geofeed",
            "type": "application/geofeed+csv"
        },
        ...
    ],
    ...
}]]></sourcecode>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="operational-considerations"><name>Operational Considerations</name>
<t>When an RDAP client performs an IP network lookup, per <xref target="RFC9082" sectionFormat="of" section="3.1.1"></xref>, the RDAP server is required to return
the most-specific IP network object that covers the IP address range provided by the client. That IP network object may
not have an associated geofeed link, but it is possible that a less-specific IP network object does have such a link.
Clients attempting to retrieve geofeed data for a given IP address range via RDAP should consider whether to retrieve
the parent object for the initial response (and so on, recursively) in the event that the initial response does not
contain geofeed data. Conversely, server operators should consider interface options for resource holders in order to
support the provisioning of geofeed links for all networks covered by the associated data.</t>
<t>It is common for a resource holder to maintain a single geofeed file containing the geofeed data for all of their
resources. The resource holder then updates each of their network object registrations to refer to that single geofeed
file. As with geofeed references in inetnum: objects (per <xref target="RFC9632"></xref>), clients who find a geofeed link object within an
IP network object and opt to retrieve the data from the associated link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore any entry where the entry's IP
address range is outside the IP network object's address range.</t>
<t><xref target="RFC8805" sectionFormat="of" section="3.2"></xref> recommends that consumers of geofeed data verify that the publisher of the data is
authoritative for the relevant resources. The RDAP bootstrap process <xref target="RFC9224"></xref> helps clients with this
recommendation, since a client following that process will be directed to the RDAP server that is able to make
authoritative statements about the disposition of the relevant resources.</t>
<t>To prevent undue load on RDAP and geofeed servers, clients fetching geofeed data using these mechanisms <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> do
frequent real-time lookups. See <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="6"></xref> for further details.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="privacy-considerations"><name>Privacy Considerations</name>
<t>All the privacy considerations from <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="7"></xref> apply to this document. In particular, the service provider
publishing the geofeed file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> take care not to expose the location of any individual.</t>
<t>Many jurisdictions have laws or regulations that restrict the use of &quot;personal data&quot;, per the definition in <xref target="RFC6973"></xref>.
Given that, registry operators should ascertain whether the regulatory environment in which they operate permits
implementation of the functionality defined in this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security_considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>Sections <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="bare" section="6" /> and
<xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="bare" section="9" /> of <xref target="RFC9632"/>
document several security considerations that are equally relevant in the RDAP context.</t>
<t>A geofeed file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be referenced with an HTTPS URL, per <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="6"></xref>. The geofeed file may also contain an
RPKI signature, per <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="5"></xref>.</t>
<t>Besides that, this document does not introduce any new security considerations past those already discussed in the RDAP
protocol specifications (<xref target="RFC7481"></xref>, <xref target="RFC9560"></xref>).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>

<section anchor="rdap-extensions-registry"><name>RDAP Extensions Registry</name>
<t>IANA has registered the following value in the "RDAP Extensions" registry at <xref target="RDAP-EXTENSIONS"></xref>:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
  <dt>Extension Identifier:</dt><dd>geofeed1</dd>
  <dt>Registry Operator:</dt><dd>Any</dd>
  <dt>Specification:</dt><dd>RFC 9877</dd>
  <dt>Contact:</dt><dd>IETF &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</dd>
  <dt>Intended Usage:</dt><dd>This extension describes version 1 of a method to access the IP geolocation feed data through RDAP.</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="link_relations_registry"><name>Link Relations Registry</name>
<t>IANA has registered the following value in the "Link Relations" registry at <xref target="LINK-RELATIONS"></xref>:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
  <dt>Relation Name:</dt><dd>geofeed</dd>
  <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Refers to a resource with IP geofeed location information related to the link context.</dd>
  <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9877</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="media_types_registry"><name>Media Types Registry</name>
<t>IANA has registered the following media type in the "Media Types" registry at <xref target="MEDIA-TYPES"></xref>:</t>

<dl spacing="normal" newline="false">
  <dt>Type name:</dt><dd>application</dd>
  <dt>Subtype name:</dt><dd>geofeed+csv</dd>
  <dt>Required parameters:</dt><dd>N/A</dd>
  <dt>Optional parameters:</dt><dd>&quot;charset&quot; is an optional
  parameter for &quot;text/csv&quot;, but it is not used for
  &quot;application/geofeed+csv&quot; because the geofeed content is always in
  UTF-8 (<xref target="RFC8805" sectionFormat="of"
  section="2.1"></xref>).</dd>
  <dt>Encoding considerations:</dt><dd>See <xref target="RFC9632" sectionFormat="of" section="2"></xref>.</dd>
  <dt>Security considerations:</dt><dd>See <xref target="security_considerations"></xref> of RFC 9877.</dd>
  <dt>Interoperability considerations:</dt><dd>There are no known interoperability problems regarding this media format.</dd>
  <dt>Published specification:</dt><dd>RFC 9877.</dd>
  <dt>Applications that use this media type:</dt><dd>Implementations of the
  Registration Data Access Protocol (RDAP) Extension for Geofeed
  Data. Furthermore, any application that processes the CSV geofeed data.</dd>
  <dt>Additional information:</dt><dd>This media type is a product of the IETF
  REGEXT Working Group. The REGEXT charter, information on the REGEXT mailing
  list, and other documents produced by the REGEXT Working Group can be found
  at <xref target="REGEXT"></xref>.</dd>
  <dt>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:</dt><dd><br/>REGEXT Working Group &lt;regext@ietf.org&gt;</dd>
  <dt>Intended usage:</dt><dd>COMMON</dd>
  <dt>Restrictions on usage:</dt><dd>None</dd>
  <dt>Authors:</dt><dd>Tom Harrison, Jasdip Singh</dd>
  <dt>Author/Change controller:</dt><dd>IETF</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="structured_syntax_suffixes_registry"><name>Structured Syntax Suffixes Registry</name>
<t>IANA has registered the following value in the "Structured Syntax Suffixes" registry
at <xref target="STRUCTURED-SYNTAX-SUFFIXES"></xref>:</t>

<dl spacing="normal" newline="false">
  <dt>Name:</dt><dd>Comma-Separated Values (CSV)</dd>
  <dt>+suffix:</dt><dd>+csv</dd>
  <dt>References:</dt><dd><xref target="RFC4180"></xref>, <xref target="RFC7111"></xref></dd>
  <dt>Encoding Considerations:</dt><dd>Same as &quot;text/csv&quot;.</dd>
  <dt>Interoperability Considerations:</dt><dd>Same as &quot;text/csv&quot;.</dd>
  <dt>Fragment Identifier Considerations:</dt>
  <dd><t>The syntax and semantics of fragment identifiers specified for +csv <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be as specified for &quot;text/csv&quot;.</t>
  <t>The syntax and semantics for fragment identifiers for a specific &quot;xxx/yyy+csv&quot; <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be processed as follows:</t>
  <ul spacing="compact">
    <li>For cases defined in +csv, where the fragment identifier resolves per
    the +csv rules, then as specified for +csv.</li> <li>For cases defined in
    +csv, where the fragment identifier does not resolve per the +csv rules,
    then as specified for &quot;xxx/&wj;yyy+csv&quot;.</li>
    <li>For cases not defined in +csv, then as specified for &quot;xxx/&wj;yyy+csv&quot;.</li>
  </ul></dd>
  <dt>Security Considerations:</dt><dd>Same as &quot;text/csv&quot;.</dd>
  <dt>Contact:</dt><dd>IETF &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</dd>
  <dt>Author/Change controller:</dt><dd>IETF</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>


</middle>

<back>
<references><name>References</name>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9082.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9083.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9224.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9632.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<reference anchor="LINK-RELATIONS" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/">
  <front>
    <title>Link Relations</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IANA</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="MEDIA-TYPES" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">
  <front>
    <title>Media Types</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IANA</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="RDAP-EXTENSIONS" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/rdap-extensions/">
  <front>
    <title>RDAP Extensions</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IANA</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="REGEXT" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/regext/">
  <front>
    <title>Registration Protocols Extensions (regext)</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IETF</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2622.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4180.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6838.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7111.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7480.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7481.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8805.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9560.xml"/>
<reference anchor="STRUCTURED-SYNTAX-SUFFIXES" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-type-structured-suffix/">
  <front>
    <title>Structured Syntax Suffixes</title>
    <author>
      <organization>IANA</organization>
    </author>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>
</references>


<section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t><contact fullname="Mark Kosters"/> provided initial support and
encouragement for this work, along with the authors of <xref target="RFC9632"></xref>. <contact fullname="Gavin Brown"/> suggested using a web link instead
of a simple URL string to specify a geofeed file URL. <contact fullname="Andy
Newton"/>, <contact fullname="James Gould"/>, <contact fullname="Scott
Hollenbeck"/>, <contact fullname="Mario Loffredo"/>, <contact fullname="Orie
Steele"/>, <contact fullname="Alexey Melnikov"/>, <contact fullname="Mark
Nottingham"/>, <contact fullname="Rifaat Shekh-Yusef"/>, <contact
fullname="Dale R. Worley"/>, <contact fullname="Dhruv Dhody"/>, <contact
fullname="Mohamed Boucadair"/>, <contact fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani"/>,
<contact fullname="Ketan Talaulikar"/>, and <contact fullname="Éric Vyncke"/>
provided valuable feedback for this document.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
