<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" number="9948" docName="draft-alvestrand-protocol-police-00" category="info" updates="" obsoletes="" submissionType="independent" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3" xml:lang="en">

<!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.32.0 -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPP Schedule of Punishments">Internet Protocol Police (IPP) - Schedule of Punishments</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9948"/>
    <author fullname="Graham Reuben Beard" initials="G.R." surname="Beard">
      <organization>Internet Protocol Police</organization>
      <address>
        <email>greybeard@stupid.domain.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Oldham F. Art" initials="O.F." surname="Art">
      <organization>Internet Protocol Police</organization>
      <address>
        <email>oldfart@stupid.domain.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Harald T. Alvestrand" initials="H" surname="Alvestrand" role="editor">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>harald@alvestrand.no</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2026" month="April" day="1"/>
    <keyword>internet protocol police</keyword>
    <abstract>

<t>The Internet Protocol Police (IPP) is in charge of punishing willful infractions of the
Collected Wisdom of the IETF community.
      This document sets out the schedule of punishments for such infractions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

<section anchor="introduction">
  <name>Introduction</name>


<t>The Internet Protocol Police (IPP) <xref target="RFC8962"/> has long served
as an unifying force for maintaining the Internet Architectural Principles and
the Rules of Sanity. The IPP has a harsh schedule for punishing infractions
of these Principles and Rules. The schedule has served the IETF community
well being applied in an informal manner, but the community has complained
that the punishments are served indiscriminately and unaccountably. Therefore,
this document publishes the schedule for the enlightenment of everyone in the
IETF community, especially newcomers.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>

<t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>

<t>In addition, the key words defined in <xref target="RFC6919"/> MIGHT apply.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="schedule-of-punishments">
      <name>Schedule of Punishments</name>
      <t>These punishments are meted out after due consideration of infractions of the Principles and Rules.
Due to the time required to reach consensus in the IPP about the need for these punishments,
the punishments are usually applied late in the process, frequently as previous flawed efforts
      are brought up as examples to follow for new work.</t>

      <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
      <dt><strong>The Raised Eyebrow</strong></dt>
      <dd>This is a punishment for lesser infractions, such as bad grammar, dangling participles, and
inconsistent terminology.</dd>
      <dt><strong>The Frown</strong></dt>
      <dd>This punishment is reserved for more dire infractions, such as using a codepoint from an
IANA-managed namespace without registering it, state tables that have dead ends, or
ABNF to describe syntax that cannot be parsed by any parsing technology known
in the year 1993.</dd>
      <dt><strong>The Shaking of the Head</strong></dt>
      <dd>This punishment is reserved for infractions involving complexity swept under the carpet,
such as invoking the case-fold operation without a Unicode considerations section or
marking critical parts as "implementation defined".</dd>
      <dt><strong>The Finger Wag</strong></dt>
      <dd>This punishment is reserved for the infractions described in <xref target="RFC4041"/>.</dd>
      <dt><strong>The Head-in-Hand Gesture</strong></dt>
      <dd>This mythical punishment has been rumored to have been invoked by the first greybeard
to fully understand the implications of HTML/HTTP. However, the gravity of the gesture
      has precluded its application to more common cases.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="percussive-persuasion-during-protocol-development">
      <name>Percussive Persuasion During Protocol Development</name>
      
<t>While a protocol is being developed, random greybeards may perform actions resembling the
punishments defined in <xref target="schedule-of-punishments"/> while attempting to steer misguided
younglings onto the Path of Wisdom.
However, such guidance is more commonly applied in the form of verbal utterances, a sampling
of which are described in the following subsections. Newcomers to the process are well advised to take careful notice
when these occur during protocol development; however, these utterances are <em>not</em>, by themselves,
punishments.</t>

        <t>Despite rumors, the percussive application of a wet noodle has never been considered
an appropriate part of persuasive measures.</t>

      <section anchor="this-part-needs-elaboration" toc="exclude">
        <name>"This part needs elaboration."</name>
        <t>This guidance needs no elaboration.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="you-may-have-failed-to-consider-" toc="exclude">
        <name>"You may have failed to consider ..."</name>
        <t>I see a way to attack your protocol, and you have no defense against it.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="the-threat-model-seems-underdeveloped" toc="exclude">
        <name>"The threat model seems underdeveloped."</name>
        <t>If you explain the whole thing again, perhaps you will understand why it's
totally unworkable without me having to understand it.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="this-may-work-in-the-lab-but-" toc="exclude">
        <name>"This may work in the lab, but ..."</name>
        <t>Operational considerations are either missing or hopelessly naive.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="you-have-not-thought-this-through" toc="exclude">
        <name>"You have not thought this through."</name>
        <t>Go home and start over.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="recidivism-studies">
      <name>Recidivism Studies</name>
      
      <t>The study of repeat offenders has some methodological difficulties, such as the tendency
of excitable individuals to abandon the IETF upon repeated percussive persuasion, but recidivism is
      believed to compare reasonably with that of the US prison system (66%) <xref target="RECIDIVISM"/>.</t>
      <t>One contributing factor to this relatively low observed incidence may be the educative value of footguns;
once people have realized that the hole in their foot is in fact the result of ignoring percussive persuasion, they
may be more inclined to heed advice in later iterations.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>

      
<t>Due to the nature of this memo, it establishes an Epimenides 
Paradox Field <xref target="EPIMENIDES"/> for its subject matter, thereby
preventing any harm to the Internet from being caused by its publication.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
      <t>Unfortunately, IANA procedures do not include excursions into the imaginary
plane, so the possibility of consulting the IPP before assigning controversial numbers
is precluded. However, the IPP enjoys positive relationships with multiple
designated experts <xref target="RFC8126"/>, so the situation is not unsalvageable.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references anchor="sec-combined-references">
      <name>References</name>
      <references anchor="sec-normative-references">
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8962.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6919.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references anchor="sec-informative-references">
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4041.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>

	<reference anchor="EPIMENIDES">
	  <front>
	  <title>Mathematical Logic as Based on the Theory of Types</title>
	  <author initials="B." surname="Russell" fullname="Bertrand Russell">
	  </author>
	  <date year="1908" month="July"/>
	    </front>
	    <refcontent>American Journal of Mathematics, Volume 30, Number 3, pages 222-262</refcontent>
</reference>

	<reference anchor="RECIDIVISM" target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=5029176">
	  <front>
	    <title>Does the United States Have High Recidivism Rates? New Data Raise Questions About Prevailing Beliefs</title>
	    <author initials="B." surname="Latzer" fullname="Barry Latzer">
	      <organization>City University of New York - John Jay College of Criminal Justice</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date year="2024" month="November" day="15"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.2139/ssrn.5029176 "/>
	</reference>
      </references>
    </references>

<section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgments">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The development of this document was greatly facilitated by a comfortable keyboard and
a bout of insomnia. However, a few contributing individuals, listed here in alphabetical order,
deserve to be called out:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t><contact fullname="Aaron Falk"/></t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><contact fullname="Adrian Farrel"/></t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><contact fullname="John Klensin"/></t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><contact fullname="Craig Partridge"/></t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><contact fullname="Martin Thomson"/></t>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
