<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-idr-sr-policy-safi-13" number="9830" ipr="trust200902" consensus="true" updates="9012" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Segment Routing Policies in BGP">Advertising Segment
    Routing Policies in BGP</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9830"/>
    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." surname="Previdi">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>
        <email>stefano@previdi.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C." surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Brussels</city>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" initials="K." role="editor" surname="Talaulikar">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ketant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Paul Mattes" initials="P." surname="Mattes">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pamattes@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dhanendra Jain" initials="D." surname="Jain">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dhanendra.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year="2025"/>
    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>idr</workgroup>



    <abstract>
      <t>A Segment Routing (SR) Policy is an ordered list of segments (also
      referred to as "instructions") that define a source-routed policy. An SR
      Policy consists of one or more Candidate Paths (CPs), each comprising one or
      more segment lists. A headend can be provisioned with these CPs using various mechanisms such as Command-Line Interface (CLI), Network Configuration Protocol (NETCONF), Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP), or BGP.</t>
      <t>This document specifies how BGP can be used to distribute SR Policy
      CPs. It introduces a BGP SAFI for advertising a CP of an SR Policy and defines sub-TLVs for the Tunnel Encapsulation
      Attribute to signal information related to these CPs.</t>
      <t>Furthermore, this document updates RFC 9012 by extending the Color
      Extended Community to support additional steering modes over SR
      Policy.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="INTRO" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Segment Routing (SR) <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/> allows a headend node
      to steer a packet flow along a specific path. Intermediate per-path
      states are eliminated thanks to source routing.</t>
      <t>The headend node is said to steer a flow into an SR Policy <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The packets steered into an SR Policy carry an ordered list of
      segments associated with that SR Policy.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/> further details the concepts of SR Policy
      and steering into an SR Policy. These apply equally to the SR-MPLS and
      Segment Routing over IPv6 (SRv6) data plane instantiations of Segment
      Routing using SR-MPLS and SRv6 Segment Identifiers (SIDs) as described
      in <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>. <xref target="RFC8660" format="default"/> describes the
      representation and processing of this ordered list of segments as an
      MPLS label stack for SR-MPLS. <xref target="RFC8754" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> describe the same for SRv6 with the use of the
      Segment Routing Header (SRH).</t>
      <t>The functionality related to SR Policy described in <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/> can be conceptually viewed as being incorporated in
      an SR Policy Module (SRPM). The following is a reminder of the high-level
      functionality of SRPM: </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>Learning multiple CPs for an SR Policy via
          various mechanisms (CLI, NETCONF, PCEP, or BGP).</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Selection of the best CP for an SR Policy.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Associating a Binding SID (BSID) to the selected CP
          of an SR Policy.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Installation of the selected CP and its BSID in the
          forwarding plane.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document specifies the use of BGP to distribute one or more of
      the CPs of an SR Policy to the headend of that SR Policy. The
      document describes the functionality provided by BGP and, as
      appropriate, provides references for the functionality, which is outside
      the scope of BGP (i.e., resides within SRPM on the headend node).</t>
      <t>This document specifies a way of representing SR Policy CPs in BGP UPDATE messages. BGP can then be used to propagate the SR
      Policy CPs to the headend nodes in a network. The usual BGP
      rules for BGP propagation and best-path selection are used. At the
      headend of a specific SR Policy, this will result in one or more CPs being installed into the "BGP table". These paths are then passed
      to the SRPM. The SRPM may compare them to CPs learned via
      other mechanisms and will choose one or more paths to be installed in
      the data plane. BGP itself does not install SR Policy CPs
      into the data plane.</t>
      <t>This document introduces a BGP Subsequent Address Family Identifier (SAFI) for
      IPv4 and IPv6 address families. In BGP UPDATE messages of those AFI/SAFIs,
      the Network Layer Reachability Information (NLRI) identifies an SR
      Policy CP while the attributes encode the segment lists and
      other details of that SR Policy CP.</t>
      <t>While, for simplicity, the text in this document states that BGP
      advertises an SR Policy, it is to be understood that BGP advertises a
      CP of an SR Policy and that this SR Policy might have
      several other CPs provided via BGP (via an NLRI with a
      different distinguisher as defined in <xref target="SRPOLICYSAFI" format="default"/>),
      PCEP, NETCONF, or local policy configuration.</t>
      <t>Typically, an SR Policy Controller <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/> defines
      the set of policies and advertises them to SR Policy headend routers
      (typically ingress routers). These SR Policy advertisements use the BGP
      extensions defined in this document. In most cases, the SR Policy
      advertisement is tailored for a specific SR Policy headend; consequently,
      it may be transmitted over a direct BGP session (i.e., without
      intermediate BGP hops) to that headend and is not propagated any
      further. In such cases, the SR Policy advertisements will not traverse any
      Route Reflector (RR) (see <xref target="RFC4456" format="default"/> and <xref target="PROPAGATE" format="default"/>).</t>
      
      <t>Alternatively, a BGP egress router may advertise SR Policies that
      represent paths that terminate on it. In such cases, the router can
      send these policies directly to each headend over a dedicated BGP
      session, without necessitating any further propagation of the
      SR Policy.</t>
      <t>In some situations, it is undesirable for a controller or BGP egress
      router to have a BGP session to each SR Policy headend. In these
      situations, BGP RRs may be used to propagate the
      advertisements. In certain other deployments, it may be necessary for
      the advertisement to propagate through a sequence of one or more Autonomous Systems (ASes)
      within an SR Domain (refer to <xref target="Security" format="default"/> for the
      associated security considerations). To make this possible, an attribute
      needs to be attached to the advertisement that enables a BGP speaker to
      determine whether it is intended to be a headend for the advertised
      SR Policy. This is done by attaching one or more Route Target extended
      communities to the advertisement <xref target="RFC4360" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The BGP extensions for the advertisement of SR Policies include
      following components: </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>A SAFI whose NLRIs
          identify an SR Policy CP.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>A Tunnel Type identifier for SR Policy and a set of sub-TLVs to
          be inserted into the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute (as defined in
          <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>) specifying segment lists of the SR Policy
          CP as well as other information about the SR
          Policy.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>One or more IPv4 address-specific format Route Target extended
          community (<xref target="RFC4360" format="default"/>) attached to the SR Policy
          CP advertisement that indicates the intended headend
          of such an SR Policy CP advertisement.</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>The SR Policy SAFI route updates utilize the Tunnel Encapsulation
      Attribute to signal an SR Policy, which itself functions as a tunnel.
      This usage differs notably from the approach described in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>, where the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute is
      associated with a BGP route update (e.g., for Internet or VPN routes) to
      specify the tunnel used for forwarding traffic. This document does not
      modify or supersede the usage of the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute for
      existing AFI/SAFIs as defined in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>. Details
      regarding the processing of the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute for the
      SR Policy SAFI are provided in Sections <xref target="ENCAPSATTR" format="counter"/> and <xref target="ENDCOLOR" format="counter"/>.</t>
      <t>The northbound advertisement of the operational state of the SR
      Policy CPs as part of BGP - Link State (BGP-LS) <xref target="RFC9552" format="default"/>
      topology information is specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-sr-policy" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The signaling of Dynamic and Composite CPs (Sections
      <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="bare" section="5.2"/> and <xref
      target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="bare" section="5.3"/>, respectively, of
      <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>) is outside the scope of this
      document.</t>
      <t>The Color Extended Community (as defined in <xref target="RFC9012"
      format="default"/>) is used to steer traffic into an SR Policy, as
      described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of"
      section="8.8"/>. <xref target="EXTCOLOR" format="default"/> of this
      document updates <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/> with
      modifications to the format of the Flags field of the Color Extended
      Community by using the two leftmost bits of that field.</t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ENCODING" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SR Policy Encoding</name>
      <section anchor="SRPOLICYSAFI" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy SAFI and NLRI</name>
        <t>The SR Policy SAFI with
        code point 73 is introduced in this document. The AFI used <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be IPv4(1) or IPv6(2).</t>
        <t>The SR Policy SAFI uses the NLRI format defined as follows: </t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy SAFI Format</name>
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
+------------------+
|  NLRI Length     | 1 octet
+------------------+
|  Distinguisher   | 4 octets
+------------------+
|  Color           | 4 octets
+------------------+
|  Endpoint        | 4 or 16 octets
+------------------+
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Where:</t>
        <dl spacing="normal">
          <dt>NLRI Length:</dt><dd>1 octet indicating the length expressed in bits as
          defined in <xref target="RFC4760" format="default"/>. When AFI = 1,
          the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 96; when AFI = 2, the value
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 192.</dd>

	  
          <dt>Distinguisher:</dt><dd><t>4-octet value uniquely identifying the SR Policy in
          the context of &lt;Color, Endpoint&gt; tuple. The distinguisher has
          no semantic value.  It is used by the SR Policy originator to form
          unique NLRIs the following situations:</t>
	  <ul spacing="normal">
	    <li>to differentiate multiple CPs
            of the same SR Policy</li>
	    <li>to differentiate CPs meant for different headends but having the same Color and Endpoint</li>
	  </ul>
<t>The distinguisher is
          the discriminator of the SR Policy CP as specified in
          <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.5"/>.</t></dd>
          <dt>Color:</dt><dd>4 octets that carry an unsigned non-zero integer
          value indicating the Color of the SR Policy as specified in <xref
          target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1"/>. The Color is
          used to match the Color of the destination prefixes to steer traffic
          into the SR Policy as specified in <xref target="RFC9256"
          sectionFormat="of" section="8"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Endpoint:</dt><dd>a value that identifies the Endpoint of an SR Policy. The
          Endpoint may represent a single node or a set of nodes (e.g., an
          anycast address). The Endpoint is an IPv4 (4-octet) address or an
          IPv6 (16-octet) address according to the AFI of the NLRI. The
          address can be either unicast or an unspecified address (0.0.0.0
          for IPv4, :: for IPv6), known as a null Endpoint as specified in
          <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1"/>.</dd>
        </dl>

        <t>The Color and Endpoint are used to automate the steering of BGP
        service routes on an SR Policy as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="8"/>.</t>
        <t>The NLRI containing an SR Policy CP is carried in a BGP
        UPDATE message <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/> using BGP multiprotocol
        extensions <xref target="RFC4760" format="default"/> with an AFI of 1 or 2 (IPv4 or
        IPv6) and with a SAFI of 73. The fault management and error handling
        in the encoding of the NLRI are specified in <xref target="ERROR" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>A BGP UPDATE message that carries the MP_REACH_NLRI or MP_UNREACH_NLRI
        attribute with the SR Policy SAFI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also carry the BGP mandatory
        attributes. In addition, the BGP UPDATE message <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also contain any
        of the BGP optional attributes.</t>
        <t>The next-hop network address field in SR Policy SAFI (73) updates
        may be either a 4-octet IPv4 address or a 16-octet IPv6 address,
        independent of the SR Policy AFI. The Length field of the next-hop
        address specifies the next-hop address family. If the next-hop length
        is 4, then the next-hop is an IPv4 address. If the next-hop length is
        16, then it is a global IPv6 address.  If the next-hop length is 32,
        then it has a global IPv6 address followed by a link-local IPv6
        address. The setting of the next-hop field and its attendant
        processing is governed by standard BGP procedures as described in
        <xref target="RFC4760" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/> and <xref target="RFC2545" sectionFormat="of" section="3"/>.</t>
        <t>It is important to note that at any BGP speaker receiving BGP
        updates with SR Policy NLRIs, the SRPM processes only the best path as
        per the BGP best-path selection algorithm. In other words, this
        document leverages the existing BGP propagation and best-path
        selection rules. Details of the procedures are described in <xref target="OPERATIONS" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>It has to be noted that if several CPs of the same SR
        Policy (Endpoint, Color) are signaled via BGP to a headend, then it is
        <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that each NLRI use a different distinguisher. If BGP has
        installed into the BGP table two advertisements whose respective NLRIs
        have the same Color and Endpoint, but different distinguishers, both
        advertisements are passed to the SRPM as different CPs
        along with their respective originator information (i.e., Autonomous System Number (ASN) and BGP
        Router-ID) as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.4"/>.
        The ASN would be the ASN of the origin and the BGP Router-ID is
        determined in the following order:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>
            <t>From the Route Origin Community <xref target="RFC4360" format="default"/> if
            present and carrying an IP Address, or</t>
          </li>
          <li>
	    
            <t>As the BGP ORIGINATOR_ID <xref target="RFC4456" format="default"/> if present,
            or</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>As the BGP Router-ID of the peer from which the update was
            received as a last resort.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t><xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.9"/> specifies the selection
        of the active CP of the SR Policy by the SRPM based on the
        information provided to it by BGP.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ENCAPSATTR" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy and Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute</name>

        <t>The content of the SR Policy CP is encoded in the
        Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute defined in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>
        using a Tunnel Type called the "SR Policy" type with code point 15. The use
        of the SR Policy Tunnel Type is applicable only for the AFI/SAFI pairs of
        (1/73, 2/73). This document specifies the use of the Tunnel
        Encapsulation Attribute with the SR Policy Tunnel Type and the use of
        any other Tunnel Type with the SR Policy SAFI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered
        malformed and handled by the "treat-as-withdraw" strategy <xref target="RFC7606" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>The SR Policy Encoding structure is as follows: </t>

	<figure>
	  <name>SR Policy Encoding</name>
        <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
SR Policy SAFI NLRI: <Distinguisher, Color, Endpoint>
Attributes:
   Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute (23)
      Tunnel Type: SR Policy (15)
          Binding SID
          Preference
          Priority
          SR Policy Name
          SR Policy Candidate Path Name
          Explicit NULL Label Policy (ENLP)
          Segment List
              Weight
              Segment
              Segment
              ...
          ...
]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Where:</t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
	  <li>
            <t>The SR Policy SAFI NLRI is defined in <xref target="SRPOLICYSAFI" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute is defined in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>The Tunnel Type is set to 15.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Preference, Binding SID, Priority, SR Policy Name, SR Policy
            Candidate Path Name, ENLP, Segment-List, Weight, and Segment
            sub-TLVs are defined in <xref target="SRPOLICYTLV" format="default"/>.</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Additional sub-TLVs may be defined in the future.</t>
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>A Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain more than one TLV
        of type "SR Policy"; such updates <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered malformed and
        handled by the "treat-as-withdraw" strategy <xref target="RFC7606" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>BGP does not need to perform the validation of the tunnel (i.e., SR
        Policy) itself as indicated in <xref target="RFC9012" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.
        The validation of the SR Policy information that is advertised using
        the sub-TLVs specified in <xref target="SRPOLICYTLV" format="default"/> is performed by
        the SRPM.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ENDCOLOR" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Applicability of Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Sub-TLVs</name>
        <t>The Tunnel Egress Endpoint and Color sub-TLVs of the Tunnel
        Encapsulation Attribute, as defined in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>, are
        not utilized for SR Policy encodings. Consequently, their values are
        not relevant within the context of the SR Policy SAFI NLRI. If these
        sub-TLVs are present, a BGP speaker <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore them and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> remove
        them from the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute during propagation.</t>
        <t>Similarly, any other sub-TLVs, including those specified in <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>, that do not have explicitly defined applicability
        to the SR Policy SAFI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the BGP speaker and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
        removed from the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute during
        propagation.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="SRPOLICYTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy Sub-TLVs</name>
        <t>This section specifies the sub-TLVs defined for encoding the
        information about the SR Policy Candidate Path.</t>
        <t>Preference, Binding SID, SRv6 Binding SID, Segment-List, Priority,
        SR Policy Name, SR Policy Candidate Path Name, and Explicit NULL Label
        Policy are all optional sub-TLVs introduced for the BGP Tunnel
        Encapsulation Attribute <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/> being defined in this
        section.</t>
        <t>Weight and Segment are sub-TLVs of the Segment-List sub-TLV
        mentioned above.</t>
        <t>An early draft version of this document included only the Binding SID
        sub-TLV that could be used for both SR-MPLS and SRv6 BSIDs. The
        SRv6 Binding SID TLV was introduced in later versions to support the
        advertisement of additional SRv6 capabilities without affecting
        backward compatibility for early implementations.</t>
        <t>The fault management and error handling in the encoding of the
        sub-TLVs defined in this section are specified in <xref target="ERROR" format="default"/>. For the TLVs/sub-TLVs that are specified as single
        instance, only the first instance of that TLV/sub-TLV is used: the
        other instances <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> considered to be
        malformed.</t>
        <t>None of the sub-TLVs defined in the following subsections have any
        effect on the BGP best-path selection or propagation procedures. These
        sub-TLVs are not used by the BGP path selection process and are
        instead passed on to SRPM as SR Policy Candidate Path information for
        further processing as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2"/>.</t>
        <t>The use of SR Policy sub-TLVs is applicable only for the AFI/SAFI
        pairs of (1/73, 2/73). Future documents may extend their applicability
        to other AFI/SAFI.</t>
        <section anchor="PREFTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Preference Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>The Preference sub-TLV is used to carry the Preference of an SR
          Policy CP. The contents of this sub-TLV are used by the
          SRPM as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.7"/>.</t>
          <t>The Preference sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more
          than once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>The Preference sub-TLV has the following format: </t>

	  <figure>
	    <name>Preference Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Preference (4 octets)                    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	  </figure>
	  
	  <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>12</dd>
            
            <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 6.</dd>
           
            
              <dt>Flags:</dt><dd>1 octet of flags. No flags are defined in this
              document. The Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero on transmission
              and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
              <dt>Preference:</dt><dd>a 4-octet value indicating the Preference of the
              SR Policy CP as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.7"/>.</dd>
          
          </dl>

        </section>
        <section anchor="BINDINGSIDTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Binding SID Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>The Binding SID sub-TLV is used to signal the BSID-related
          information of the SR Policy CP. The contents of this
          sub-TLV are used by the SRPM as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="6"/>.</t>
          <t>The Binding SID sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more
          than once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>When the Binding SID sub-TLV is used to signal an SRv6 SID, the
          selection of the corresponding SRv6 Endpoint Behavior <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> to be instantiated is determined by the headend
          node. It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV, as
          defined in <xref target="SRV6BINDINGSIDTLV" format="default"/>, be used when signaling an SRv6 BSID
          for an SR Policy CP. The support for the use of this
          Binding SID sub-TLV for the signaling of an SRv6 BSID is retained
          primarily for backward compatibility with implementations that
          followed early draft versions of this document that had not defined the
          SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV.</t>
          <t>The Binding SID sub-TLV has the following format: </t>

	  <figure>
	    <name>Binding SID Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              Binding SID (variable, optional)                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
	  <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>13</dd>
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 18 when a SRv6 BSID is present, 6 when an SR-MPLS
              BSID is present, or 2 when no BSID is present.</dd>
              <dt>Flags:</dt><dd><t>1 octet of flags. The following flags are defined in
              the registry "SR Policy Binding SID Flags" as described in <xref target="IANABSIDFLAGS" format="default"/>:</t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy Binding SID Flags</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|S|I|           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
              <t>Where:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                
                  <li>The S-Flag encodes the "Specified-BSID-Only"
                  behavior. It is used by SRPM as described in <xref
                  target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="6.2.3"/>.</li>
                  <li>The I-Flag encodes the "Drop-Upon-Invalid" 
                  behavior. It is used by SRPM as described in <xref
                  target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="8.2"/> to
                  define a specific SR Policy forwarding behavior. The flag
                  indicates that the SR Policy is to perform the "Drop-Upon-Invalid" behavior when no valid CP is
                  available for this SR Policy. In this situation, the CP with
                  the highest preference amongst those with the "Drop-Upon-Invalid" behavior is made active to drop traffic steered over
                  the SR Policy.</li>
                
                
                  <li>The unassigned bits in the Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero
                  upon transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored upon receipt.
                </li>
              </ul></dd>

            
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero on
              transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.
            </dd>
            
              <dt>Binding SID:</dt><dd><t>If the length is 2, then no BSID is
              present. If the length is 6, then the BSID is encoded in 4
              octets using the format below. Traffic Class (TC), S, and TTL
              (Total of 12 bits) are RESERVED and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              be ignored.</t>

<figure>
  <name>Binding SID Label Encoding</name>
              <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Label                        | TC  |S|       TTL     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
              <t>The Label field is validated by the SRPM but <bcp14>MUST
              NOT</bcp14> contain the reserved MPLS label values (0-15). If the length
              is 18, then the BSID contains a 16-octet SRv6 SID.</t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="SRV6BINDINGSIDTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SRv6 Binding SID Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>The SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV is used to signal the SRv6-BSID-related information of an SR Policy CP. It enables
          the specification of the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior <xref
          target="RFC8986" format="default"/> to be instantiated on the
          headend node. The contents of this sub-TLV are used by the SRPM as
          described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of"
          section="6"/>.</t>
          <t>The SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>. More than one SRv6
          Binding SID sub-TLV <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be signaled in the same SR Policy encoding
          to indicate one or more SRv6 SIDs, each with potentially different
          SRv6 Endpoint Behaviors to be instantiated.</t>
          <t>The SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV has the following format:</t>

<figure>
  <name>SRv6 Binding SID Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                 SRv6 Binding SID (16 octets)                  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//     SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure (optional)     //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

	  <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>20</dd>
           
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 26 when the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure is
              present; else, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 18.</dd>
           
              <dt>Flags:</dt><dd><t>1 octet of flags. The following flags are defined in
              the registry "SR Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags" as described in
              <xref target="IANASRV6BSIDFLAGS" format="default"/>:</t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|S|I|B|         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
              <t>Where:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                  <li>The S-Flag encodes the "Specified-BSID-Only"
                  behavior. It is used by SRPM as described
                  in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="6.2.3"/>.</li>
                
                
                  <li>The I-Flag encodes the "Drop-Upon-Invalid"
                  behavior. It is used by SRPM as described in 
                  <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="8.2"/>.</li>
              
                  <li>The B-Flag, when set, indicates the presence of
                  the "SRv6 Endpoint Behavior &amp; SID Structure" encoding
                  specified in <xref target="BEHAVIORSTRUCT" format="default"/>.</li>
               
               
                  <li>The unassigned bits in the Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero
                  upon transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored upon receipt.</li>
                
              </ul></dd>
            
          
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
           
              <dt>SRv6 Binding SID:</dt><dd>Contains a 16-octet SRv6 SID. The value 0
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used when the controller wants to indicate the desired
              SRv6 Endpoint Behavior, SID Structure, or flags without
              specifying the BSID.</dd>
            
            
              <dt>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure:</dt><dd>Optional, as
              defined in <xref target="BEHAVIORSTRUCT" format="default"/>. The SRv6 Endpoint
              Behavior and SID Structure <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be included when the SRv6
              SID has not been included.</dd>
            
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="SLTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Segment List Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>The Segment List sub-TLV encodes a single explicit path towards
          the Endpoint as described in <xref target="RFC9256"
          sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>. The Segment List sub-TLV
          includes the elements of the paths (i.e., segments) as well as an
          optional Weight sub-TLV.</t>
          <t>The Segment List sub-TLV may exceed 255 bytes in length due to a
          large number of segments. A 2-octet length is thus required.
          According to <xref target="RFC9012" sectionFormat="of" section="2"/>, the sub-TLV type
          defines the size of the Length field. Therefore, for the Segment
          List sub-TLV, a code point of 128 or higher is used.</t>
          <t>The Segment List sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear multiple
          times in the SR Policy encoding. The ordering of Segment List
          sub-TLVs does not matter since each sub-TLV encodes a Segment
          List.</t>
          <t>The Segment List sub-TLV contains zero or more Segment sub-TLVs
          and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain a Weight sub-TLV.</t>
          <t>The Segment List sub-TLV has the following format: </t>

<figure>
  <name>Segment List Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |             Length            |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//                           sub-TLVs                          //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>128</dd>
            
            
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>The total length (not including the Type and Length
              fields) of the sub-TLVs encoded within the Segment List sub-TLV
              in terms of octets.</dd>
            
            
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
           
              <dt>sub-TLVs currently defined: </dt><dd>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  <t>An optional single Weight sub-TLV</t>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <t>Zero or more Segment sub-TLVs</t>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>

          <t>Validation of an explicit path encoded by the Segment List
          sub-TLV is beyond the scope of BGP and performed by the SRPM as
          described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="5"/>.</t>
          <section anchor="WEIGHTTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Weight Sub-TLV</name>
            <t>The Weight sub-TLV specifies the weight associated with a given
            segment list. The contents of this sub-TLV are used only by the
            SRPM as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.11"/>.</t>
            <t>The Weight sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than
            once inside the Segment List sub-TLV.</t>
            <t>The Weight sub-TLV has the following format: </t>

<figure>
  <name>Weight Sub-TLV</name>
            <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              Weight                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
	    </figure>

	    <t>Where:</t>
            <dl spacing="normal">
              
                <dt>Type:</dt><dd>9</dd>
              
            
                <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
                including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The
                value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 6.</dd>
             
                <dt>Flags:</dt><dd>1 octet of flags. No flags are defined in this
                document. The Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero on transmission
                and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.
              </dd>
              
                <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set
                to zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>

		
                <dt>Weight:</dt><dd>4 octets carrying an unsigned integer value indicating the
                weight associated with a segment list as described in
                <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.11"/>. A weight value of zero is
                invalid.</dd>
              
            </dl>
          </section>
          <section anchor="SEGMENTTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Segment Sub-TLVs</name>
            <t>A Segment sub-TLV describes a single segment in a segment list
            (i.e., a single element of the explicit path). One or more Segment
            sub-TLVs constitute an explicit path of the SR Policy CP. The contents of these sub-TLVs are used only by the SRPM as
            described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="4"/>.</t>
            <t>The Segment sub-TLVs are <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14> and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear multiple times
            in the Segment List sub-TLV.</t>
            <t><xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="4"/> defines several Segment
            Types:</t>
<dl>

<dt>Type A:</dt><dd>SR-MPLS Label</dd>
<dt>Type B:</dt><dd>SRv6 SID</dd>
<dt>Type C:</dt><dd>IPv4 Prefix with optional SR Algorithm</dd>
<dt>Type D:</dt><dd>IPv6 Global Prefix with optional SR Algorithm for SR-MPLS</dd>
<dt>Type E:</dt><dd>IPv4 Prefix with Local Interface ID</dd>
<dt>Type F:</dt><dd>IPv4 Addresses for link endpoints as Local, Remote pair</dd>
<dt>Type G:</dt><dd>IPv6 Prefix and Interface ID for link endpoints as Local, Remote pair for SR-MPLS</dd>
<dt>Type H:</dt><dd>IPv6 Addresses for link endpoints as Local, Remote pair for SR-MPLS</dd>
<dt>Type I:</dt><dd>IPv6 Global Prefix with optional SR Algorithm for SRv6</dd>
<dt>Type J:</dt><dd>IPv6 Prefix and Interface ID for link endpoints as Local, Remote pair for SRv6</dd>
<dt>Type K:</dt><dd>IPv6 Addresses for link endpoints as Local, Remote pair for SRv6</dd>
</dl>

            <t>The following subsections specify the sub-TLVs used for
            Segment Types A and B. The other segment types are specified in
            <xref target="RFC9831" format="default"/>. As specified in
            <xref target="RFC9256"  sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>, a mix of SR-MPLS and SRv6
            segments make the segment-list invalid.</t>
            <section anchor="TYPEA" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Segment Type A</name>
              <t>The Type A Segment sub-TLV encodes a single SR-MPLS SID. The
              format is as follows and is used to encode MPLS Label fields as
              specified in <xref target="RFC3032" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC5462" format="default"/>:
              </t>

<figure>
  <name>Type A Segment Sub-TLV</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Label                        | TC  |S|       TTL     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

	      <t>Where:</t>
              <dl spacing="normal">
                
                  <dt>Type:</dt><dd>1</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e.,
                  not including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets.
                  The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 6.</dd>
               
                  <dt>Flags:</dt><dd>1 octet of flags as defined in <xref target="SEGMENTFLAGS" format="default"/>.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                  set to zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on
                  receipt.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>Label:</dt><dd>20 bits of label value.</dd>
                  <dt>TC:</dt><dd>3 bits of traffic class.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>S:</dt><dd>1 bit of bottom-of-stack.</dd>
               
                  <dt>TTL:</dt><dd>1 octet of TTL.</dd>
                
              </dl>
              <t>The following applies to the Type-1 Segment sub-TLV:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  <t>The S bit <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be zero upon transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                  ignored upon reception.</t>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <t>If the originator wants the receiver to choose the TC
                  value, it sets the TC field to zero.</t>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <t>If the originator wants the receiver to choose the TTL
                  value, it sets the TTL field to 255.</t>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <t>If the originator wants to recommend a value for these
                  fields, it puts those values in the TC and/or TTL
                  fields.</t>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <t>The receiver <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> override the originator's values for
                  these fields. This would be determined by local policy at
                  the receiver. One possible policy would be to override the
                  fields only if the fields have the default values specified
                  above.</t>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </section>
            <section anchor="TYPEB" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Segment Type B</name>
              <t>The Type B Segment sub-TLV encodes a single SRv6 SID. The
              format is as follows: </t>

<figure>
<name>Type B Segment Sub-TLV</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//                       SRv6 SID (16 octets)                  //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//           SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure          //
//                    (optional, 8 octets)                     //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Where:</t>
              <dl spacing="normal">
              
                  <dt>Type:</dt><dd>13</dd>
                
                  <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e.,
                  not including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets.
                  The value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 26 when the SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID
                  Structure is present; else, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 18.
                </dd>
                
                  <dt>Flags:</dt><dd>1 octet of flags as defined in <xref target="SEGMENTFLAGS" format="default"/>.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                  set to zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on
                  receipt.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>SRv6 SID:</dt><dd>16 octets of IPv6 address.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure:</dt><dd>Optional, as
                  defined in <xref target="BEHAVIORSTRUCT" format="default"/>. The SRv6
                  Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be included
                  when the SRv6 SID has not been included.</dd>
               
              </dl>
              <t>The sub-TLV code point 2 defined for the advertisement of
              Segment Type B in the earlier draft versions of this document has been
              deprecated to avoid backward compatibility issues.</t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="SEGMENTFLAGS" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>SR Policy Segment Flags</name>
              <t>The Segment Type sub-TLVs described above may contain the
              following SR Policy Segment Flags in their Flags field. Also
              refer to <xref target="IANASIDFLAGS" format="default"/>: </t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy Segment Flags</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|V|   |B|       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
              <t>Where:</t>
              <ul spacing="normal">
                
                  <li> When the V-Flag is set, it is used by SRPM for "SID
                  verification" as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="5.1"/>.</li>
                
                
                  <li>When the B-Flag is set, it indicates the presence of
                  the "SRv6 Endpoint Behavior &amp; SID Structure" encoding
                  specified in <xref target="BEHAVIORSTRUCT" format="default"/>.</li>
                
                
                  <li>The unassigned bits in the Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero
                  upon transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored upon receipt.</li>
                
              </ul>

              <t>The following applies to the Segment Flags:</t>

              <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                  V-Flag applies to all Segment Types.
                </li>
                <li>
                  B-Flag applies to Segment Type B. If B-Flag appears with
                  Segment Type A, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored.
                </li>
              </ul>
            </section>
            <section anchor="BEHAVIORSTRUCT" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure</name>
              <t>The Segment Type sub-TLVs described above <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> contain the
              SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure <xref target="RFC8986" format="default"/> encoding as described below: </t>

<figure>
  <name>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior and SID Structure</name>
              <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Endpoint Behavior       |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    LB Length  |  LN Length    | Fun. Length   |  Arg. Length  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
              <t>Where:</t>
              <dl spacing="normal">
                
                  <dt>Endpoint Behavior:</dt><dd>2 octets. It carries the SRv6 Endpoint
                  Behavior code point for this SRv6 SID as defined in <xref
                  target="RFC8986" sectionFormat="of" section="10.2"/>. When
                  set with the value 0xFFFF (i.e., Opaque), the choice of SRv6
                  Endpoint Behavior is left to the headend.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>Reserved:</dt><dd>2 octets of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
                  set to zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on
                  receipt.</dd>

                
                  <dt>Locator Block Length:</dt><dd>1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Block
                  length in bits.</dd>
               
                  <dt>Locator Node Length:</dt><dd>1 octet. SRv6 SID Locator Node
                  length in bits.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>Function Length:</dt><dd>1 octet. SRv6 SID Function length in
                  bits.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>Argument Length:</dt><dd>1 octet. SRv6 SID Arguments length in
                  bits.</dd>
                
              </dl>

              <t>The total of the locator block, locator node, function, and
              argument lengths <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be less than or equal to 128.</t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="ENLPTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Explicit NULL Label Policy Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>To steer an unlabeled IP packet into an SR Policy for the MPLS
          data plane, it is necessary to push a label stack of one or more
          labels on that packet.</t>
          <t>The Explicit NULL Label Policy (ENLP) sub-TLV is used to indicate
          whether an Explicit NULL Label <xref target="RFC3032" format="default"/> must be
          pushed on an unlabeled IP packet before any other labels.</t>
          <t>If an ENLP sub-TLV is not present, the decision of whether to
          push an Explicit NULL label on a given packet is a matter of local
          configuration.</t>
          <t>The ENLP sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than
          once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>The contents of this sub-TLV are used by the SRPM as described in
          <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1"/>.</t>

<figure>
  <name>ENLP Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |     Flags     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     ENLP      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
          <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>14</dd>
          
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 3.</dd>
           
           
              <dt>Flags:</dt><dd>1 octet of flags. No flags are defined in this
              document. The Flags field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero on transmission
              and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
            
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
           
           
              <dt>ENLP (Explicit NULL Label Policy):</dt><dd><t>Indicates whether Explicit
              NULL labels are to be pushed on unlabeled IP packets that are
              being steered into a given SR Policy. The following values have
              been currently defined for this field:</t>
	      
              <dl spacing="normal" indent="6">
               
                  <dt>1:</dt><dd>Push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv4
                  packet but do not push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an
                  unlabeled IPv6 packet.</dd>
               
                  <dt>2:</dt><dd>Push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv6
                  packet but do not push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an
                  unlabeled IPv4 packet.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>3:</dt><dd>Push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv4
                  packet and push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled
                  IPv6 packet.</dd>
                
                
                  <dt>4:</dt><dd>Do not push an Explicit NULL label.</dd></dl>
		
		
              
              <t>This field can have one of the values as specified in <xref
              target="IANAENLP" format="default"/>. The ENLP unassigned values
              may be used for future extensions. Implementations adhering to
              this document <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore the ENLP sub-TLV with
              unrecognized values (viz. other than 1 through 4). The behavior
              signaled in this sub-TLV <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be overridden by
              local configuration by the network operator based on their
              deployment requirements. <xref target="RFC9256"
              sectionFormat="of" section="4.1"/> describes the behavior on the
              headend for the handling of the Explicit NULL label.</t></dd>
            
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="POLICYPRIORITY" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SR Policy Priority Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>An operator <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> set the SR Policy Priority sub-TLV to indicate the
          order in which the SR policies are recomputed upon topological
          change. The contents of this sub-TLV are used by the SRPM as
          described in <xref target="RFC9256"  sectionFormat="of" section="2.12"/>.</t>
          <t>The Priority sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than
          once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>The Priority sub-TLV has the following format:</t>

<figure>
  <name>Priority Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length      |  Priority     |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
          <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
           
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>15</dd>
            
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets.  The value
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 2.</dd>
            
              <dt>Priority:</dt><dd>A 1-octet value indicating the priority as
              specified in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.12"/>.</dd>
         
         
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="POLICYCPNAME" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SR Policy Candidate Path Name Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>An operator <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> set the SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV to
          attach a symbolic name to the SR Policy CP.</t>
          <t>Usage of the SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV is described in
          <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.6"/>.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV may exceed 255 bytes in
          length due to a long name. A 2-octet length is thus required.
          According to <xref target="RFC9012" sectionFormat="of" section="2"/>, the sub-TLV type
          defines the size of the Length field. Therefore, for the SR Policy
          Candidate Path Name sub-TLV, a code point of 128 or higher is
          used.</t>
          <t>It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the size of the symbolic name for the
          CP be limited to 255 bytes. Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose
          to truncate long names to 255 bytes when signaling via BGP.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST
          NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV has the following format:</t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy Candidate Path Name Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length                      |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//            SR Policy Candidate Path Name                     //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
          <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
            
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>129</dd>
          
          
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              is variable.</dd>
            
            
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
              <dt>SR Policy Candidate Path Name:</dt><dd>Symbolic name for the SR Policy
              CP without a NULL terminator with encoding as
              specified in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.6"/>.</dd>
            
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="POLICYNAME" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SR Policy Name Sub-TLV</name>
          <t>An operator <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> set the SR Policy Name sub-TLV to associate a
          symbolic name with the SR Policy for which the CP is
          being advertised via the SR Policy NLRI.</t>
          <t>Usage of the SR Policy Name sub-TLV is described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1"/>.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Name sub-TLV may exceed 255 bytes in length due to a
          long SR Policy name. A 2-octet length is thus required. According to
          <xref target="RFC9012" sectionFormat="of" section="2"/>, the sub-TLV
          type defines the size of the Length field. Therefore, for the SR Policy
          Name sub-TLV, a code point of 128 or higher is used.</t>
          <t>It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that the size of the symbolic name for the SR
          Policy be limited to 255 bytes. Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to
          truncate long names to 255 bytes when signaling via BGP.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Name sub-TLV is <bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>; it <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more
          than once in the SR Policy encoding.</t>
          <t>The SR Policy Name sub-TLV has the following format:</t>

<figure>
  <name>SR Policy Name Sub-TLV</name>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |   Length                      |   RESERVED    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
//                      SR Policy Name                          //
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
          <t>Where:</t>
          <dl spacing="normal">
           
              <dt>Type:</dt><dd>130</dd>
          
              <dt>Length:</dt><dd>Specifies the length of the value field (i.e., not
              including Type and Length fields) in terms of octets. The value
              is variable.</dd>
           
              <dt>RESERVED:</dt><dd>1 octet of reserved bits. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
              zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.</dd>
            
            
              <dt>SR Policy Name:</dt><dd>Symbolic name for the SR Policy without a NULL
              terminator with encoding as specified in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1"/>.</dd>
            
          </dl>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="EXTCOLOR" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Color Extended Community</name>
      <t>The Color Extended Community <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/> is used to
      steer traffic corresponding to BGP routes into an SR Policy with
      matching Color value. The Color Extended Community <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be carried in any
      BGP UPDATE message whose AFI/SAFI is 1/1 (IPv4 Unicast), 2/1 (IPv6
      Unicast), 1/4 (IPv4 Labeled Unicast), 2/4 (IPv6 Labeled Unicast), 1/128
      (VPN-IPv4 Labeled Unicast), 2/128 (VPN-IPv6 Labeled Unicast), or 25/70
      (Ethernet VPN, usually known as EVPN). Use of the Color Extended
      Community in BGP UPDATE messages of other AFI/SAFIs is not covered by
      <xref target="RFC9012" format="default"/>; hence, it is outside the scope of this document
      as well.</t>
      <t>Two bits from the Flags field of the Color Extended Community are
      used as follows to support the requirements of Color-Only steering as
      specified in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="8.8"/>: </t>

<figure>
  <name>Color Extended Community Flags</name>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                     1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|C O|        Unassigned         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

      <t>The C and O bits together form the Color-Only Type field, which
      indicates the various matching criteria between the BGP Next Hop (NH) and the SR Policy
      Endpoint in addition to the matching of the Color value. The following types
      are defined:</t>
      <dl spacing="normal">
     
          <dt>Type 0 (bits 00):</dt><dd>Specific Endpoint Match. Request a match for the
          Endpoint that is the BGP NH.</dd>
       
          <dt>Type 1 (bits 01):</dt><dd>Specific or Null Endpoint Match. Request a match
          for either the Endpoint that is the BGP NH or a null Endpoint (e.g.,
          a default gateway).</dd>
       
          <dt>Type 2 (bits 10):</dt><dd>Specific, Null, or Any Endpoint Match. Request
          a match for either the Endpoint that is the BGP NH or a null or
          any Endpoint.</dd>
     
          <dt>Type 3 (bits 11):</dt><dd>Reserved for future use and <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be used.
          Upon reception, an implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat it like Type 0.</dd>
     
      </dl>
      <t>The details of the SR Policy steering mechanisms based on these
      Color-Only types are specified in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="8.8"/>.</t>
      <t>One or more Color Extended Communities <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
      associated with a BGP route update. Sections <xref target="RFC9256"
      sectionFormat="bare" section="8.4.1"/>, <xref target="RFC9256"
      sectionFormat="bare" section="8.5.1"/>, and <xref target="RFC9256"
      sectionFormat="bare" section="8.8.2"/> of <xref target="RFC9256"
      format="default"/> specify the steering behaviors over SR Policies when
      multiple Color Extended Communities are associated with a BGP route.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="OPERATIONS" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>SR Policy Operations</name>
      <t>As mentioned in <xref target="INTRO" format="default"/>, BGP is not the actual
      consumer of an SR Policy NLRI. BGP is in charge of the origination and
      propagation of the SR Policy NLRI, but its installation and use are
      outside the scope of BGP. The details of SR Policy installation and use
      are specified in <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="CONFIG" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Advertisement of SR Policies</name>
        <t>Typically, but not limited to, an SR Policy is computed by a
        controller or a Path Computation Engine (PCE) and originated by a BGP
        speaker on its behalf.</t>
        <t>Multiple SR Policy NLRIs may be present with the same &lt;Color,
        Endpoint&gt; tuple but with different distinguishers when these SR
        policies are intended for different headends.</t>
        <t>The distinguisher of each SR Policy NLRI prevents undesired BGP
        route selection among these SR Policy NLRIs and allows their
        propagation across RRs <xref target="RFC4456" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>Moreover, one or more route targets <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be attached to the
        advertisement, where each route target identifies one or more intended
        headends for the advertised SR Policy update.</t>
        <t>If no route target is attached to the SR Policy NLRI, then it is
        assumed that the originator sends the SR Policy update directly (e.g.,
        through a BGP session) to the intended receiver. In such a case, the
        NO_ADVERTISE community <xref target="RFC1997" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be attached to
        the SR Policy update (see further details in <xref target="PROPAGATE" format="default"/>).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="RECEPT" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Reception of an SR Policy NLRI</name>
        <t>On reception of an SR Policy NLRI, a BGP speaker first determines
        if it is valid as described in <xref target="ACCEPT"
        format="default"/>; then, the BGP speaker performs the decision process for
        selection of the best route (<xref target="RFC4271" sectionFormat="of"
        section="9.1"/>). The key difference from the base BGP decision
        process is that BGP does not download the selected best routes of the SR
        Policy SAFI into the forwarding; instead, it considers them "usable"
        for passing on to the SRPM for further processing as described in
        <xref target="USABLE" format="default"/>. The selected best route is
        "propagated" (<xref target="RFC4271" sectionFormat="of"
        section="9.1.3"/>) as described in <xref target="PROPAGATE"
        format="default"/>, irrespective of its "usability" by the local
        router.</t>
        <section anchor="ACCEPT" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Validation of an SR Policy NLRI</name>
          <t>When a BGP speaker receives an SR Policy NLRI from a neighbor, it
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> first perform validation based on the following rules in
          addition to the validation described in <xref target="ERROR" format="default"/>:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
              <t>The SR Policy NLRI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a distinguisher, Color, and
              Endpoint field that implies that the length of the NLRI <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              either 12 or 24 octets (depending on the address family of the
              Endpoint).</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The SR Policy update <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have either the NO_ADVERTISE
              community, at least one Route Target extended community in
              IPv4-address format, or both. If a router supporting this
              specification receives an SR Policy update with no Route Target
              extended communities and no NO_ADVERTISE community, the update
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be considered to be malformed.</t>
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>The Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be attached to the
              BGP UPDATE message and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have a Tunnel Type TLV set to SR Policy
              (code point is 15).</t>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <t>A router that receives an SR Policy update that is not valid
          according to these criteria <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat the update as malformed, and
          the SR Policy CP <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be passed to the SRPM.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="USABLE" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Eligibility for Local Use of an SR Policy NLRI</name>
          <t>An SR Policy NLRI update that does not have a Route Target extended
          community but does have the NO_ADVERTISE community is considered
          usable.</t>
          <t>If one or more route targets are present, then at least one route
          target <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match the BGP Identifier of the receiver for the update
          to be considered usable. The BGP Identifier is defined in <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/> as a 4-octet IPv4 address and is updated by <xref target="RFC6286" format="default"/> as a 4-octet, unsigned, non-zero integer.
          Therefore, the Route Target extended community <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be of the same
          format.</t>
	  
	  
          <t>If one or more route targets are present, and none matches the
          local BGP Identifier, then, while the SR Policy NLRI is valid, the SR Policy NLRI is
          not usable on the receiver node.</t>
          <t>When the SR Policy tunnel type includes any sub-TLV that is
          unrecognized or unsupported, the update <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be considered
          usable. An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> provide an option for ignoring
          unsupported sub-TLVs.</t>
          <t>Once BGP on the receiving node has determined that the SR Policy
          NLRI is usable, it passes the SR Policy CP to the SRPM.
          Note that, along with the CP details, BGP also passes
          the originator information for breaking ties in the CP
          selection process as described in <xref target="RFC9256" sectionFormat="of" section="2.4"/>.</t>
          <t>When an update for an SR Policy NLRI results in its becoming
          unusable, BGP <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> delete its corresponding SR Policy CP
          from the SRPM.</t>
          <t>The SRPM applies the rules defined in <xref target="RFC9256"
          sectionFormat="of" section="2"/> to determine whether the SR Policy
          CP is valid and to select the active CP for
          a given SR Policy.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="PROPAGATE" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Propagation of an SR Policy</name>
          <t>SR Policy NLRIs that have the NO_ADVERTISE community attached to
          them <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be propagated.</t>
          <t>By default, a BGP node receiving an SR Policy NLRI <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
          propagate it to any External BGP (EBGP) neighbor. An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> provide an
          explicit configuration to override this and enable the propagation
          of valid SR Policy NLRIs to specific EBGP neighbors where the SR
          domain comprises multiple ASes within a single service provider
          domain (see <xref target="Security" format="default"/> for details).</t>
          <t>A BGP node advertises a received SR Policy NLRI to its Internal BGP (IBGP)
          neighbors according to normal IBGP propagation rules.</t>
          <t>By default, a BGP node receiving an SR Policy NLRI <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>
          remove the Route Target extended community before propagation. An
          implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> provide support for configuration to filter
          and/or remove the Route Target extended community before
          propagation.</t>
          <t>A BGP node <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> alter the SR Policy information carried in
          the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute during propagation.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ERROR" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Error Handling and Fault Management</name>
      <t>This section describes the error-handling actions, as described in
      <xref target="RFC7606" format="default"/>, that are to be performed for the handling of
      the BGP UPDATE messages for the BGP SR Policy SAFI.</t>
      <t>A BGP speaker <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> perform the following syntactic validation of the
      SR Policy NLRI to determine if it is malformed. This includes the
      validation of the length of each NLRI and the total length of the
      MP_REACH_NLRI and MP_UNREACH_NLRI attributes. It also includes the
      validation of the consistency of the NLRI length with the AFI and the
      endpoint address as specified in <xref target="SRPOLICYSAFI" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>When the error determined allows for the router to skip the malformed
      NLRI(s) and continue the processing of the rest of the BGP UPDATE message,
      then it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> handle such malformed NLRIs as 'treat-as-withdraw'. In
      other cases, where the error in the NLRI encoding results in the
      inability to process the BGP UPDATE message (e.g., length-related
      encoding errors), then the router <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> handle such malformed NLRIs as
      "AFI/SAFI disable" when other AFI/SAFIs besides SR Policy are being
      advertised over the same session. Alternately, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> perform
      "session reset" when the session is only being used for SR Policy or
      when a "AFI/SAFI disable" action is not possible.</t>
      <t>The validation of the TLVs/sub-TLVs introduced in this document and
      defined in their respective subsections of <xref target="SRPOLICYTLV" format="default"/>
      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be performed to determine if they are malformed or invalid. The
      validation of the Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute itself and the other
      TLVs/sub-TLVs specified in <xref target="RFC9012" sectionFormat="of" section="13"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
      be done as described in that document. In case of any error detected,
      either at the attribute or its TLV/sub-TLV level, the
      "treat-as-withdraw" strategy <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be applied. This is because an SR
      Policy update without a valid Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute (comprised
      of all valid TLVs/sub-TLVs) is not usable.</t>
      <t>An SR Policy update that is determined not to be valid (and, therefore,
      malformed) based on the rules described in <xref target="ACCEPT" format="default"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
      handled by the "treat-as-withdraw" strategy.</t>
      <t>The validation of the individual fields of the TLVs/sub-TLVs defined
      in <xref target="SRPOLICYTLV" format="default"/> are beyond the scope of BGP as they are
      handled by the SRPM as described in the individual TLV/sub-TLV
      subsections. A BGP implementation <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> perform semantic
      verification of such fields nor consider the SR Policy update to be
      invalid or not usable based on such validation.</t>
      <t>An implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> log any errors found during the above
      validation for further analysis.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      
      <t>This document uses code point allocations from the following existing
      registries in the "Subsequent Address Family Identifiers (SAFI) Parameters" registry group:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>The "SAFI Values" registry</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document uses code point allocations from the following existing registries in the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation" registry group:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>The "BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Tunnel Types" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Sub-TLVs" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "Color Extended Community Flags" registry</t>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document creates the following new
      registries in the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation" registry group: </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>The "SR Policy Segment List Sub-TLVs" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "SR Policy Binding SID Flags" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "SR Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "SR Policy Segment Flags" registry</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>The "Color Extended Community Color-Only Types" registry</t>
      </li></ul>
      <t>This document creates the following new registry in the "Segment Routing" registry group:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
          <t>The "SR Policy ENLP Values" registry</t>
        </li>
      </ul>

      
      
      <section anchor="IANASAFI" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Subsequent Address Family Identifiers (SAFI) Parameters</name>
        <t>This document registers a SAFI code point in the "SAFI Values" registry of the "Subsequent Address
        Family Identifiers (SAFI) Parameters" registry group as follows:</t>

	<table>
	  <name>BGP SAFI Code Point</name>
	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Value</th><th>Description</th><th>Reference</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td>73</td><td>SR Policy SAFI</td><td>RFC 9830</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANATUNNEL" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Tunnel Types</name>
        <t>This document registers a Tunnel Type code point in the "BGP Tunnel
        Encapsulation Attribute Tunnel Types" registry under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation" registry group.</t>

	<table>
	  <name>Tunnel Type Code Point</name>
	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Value</th><th>Description</th><th>Reference</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td>15</td><td>SR Policy</td><td>RFC 9830</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>

      </section>



      <section anchor="IANATUNNSUBTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Sub-TLVs</name>
        <t>This document defines sub-TLVs in the "BGP Tunnel
        Encapsulation Attribute Sub-TLVs" registry under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation" registry group.</t>

<table>
  <name>BGP Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute Sub-TLV Code Points</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
      <th>Change Controller</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>Preference sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>13</td>
      <td>Binding SID sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>14</td>
      <td>ENLP sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>15</td>
      <td>Priority sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>SRv6 Binding SID sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>128</td>
      <td>Segment List sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>129</td>
      <td>SR Policy Candidate Path Name sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>130</td>
      <td>SR Policy Name sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
      <td>IETF</td>
    </tr>
</tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANAEXTCOM" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Color Extended Community Flags</name>
        <t>This document defines the use of 2 bits in the
        "Color Extended Community Flags" registry under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation"
        registry group.</t>

<table>
  <name>Color Extended Community Flag Bits</name>
  <thead>
    <tr><th>Bit Position</th><th>Description</th><th>Reference</th></tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr><td>0-1</td><td>Color-only Types Field</td><td>RFC 9830</td></tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANASIDLIST" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy Segment List Sub-TLVs</name>
        <t>This document creates a new registry called "SR
        Policy Segment List Sub-TLVs" under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation"
        registry group. The registration policy of this registry is "IETF Review"
        (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The following initial sub-TLV code points are assigned by this
        document:</t>

<table>
  <name>SR Policy Segment List Sub-TLV Code Points</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Value</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Reserved</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Type A Segment sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Deprecated</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3-8</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9</td>
      <td>Weight sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10</td>
      <td>Deprecated</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>Deprecated</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>Deprecated</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>13</td>
      <td>Type B Segment sub-TLV</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>14-255</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANABSIDFLAGS" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy Binding SID Flags</name>
        <t>This document creates a new registry called "SR
        Policy Binding SID Flags" under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation"
        registry group. The registration policy of this registry is "Standards Action"
        (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The following flags are defined:</t>

<table>
  <name>SR Policy Binding SID Flags</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Specified-BSID-Only Flag (S-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>  
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Drop-Upon-Invalid Flag (I-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2-7</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANASRV6BSIDFLAGS" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags</name>
        <t>This document creates a new registry called "SR
        Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags" under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation"
        registry group. The registration policy of this registry is "Standards Action"
        (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The following flags are defined:</t>

<table>
  <name>SR Policy SRv6 Binding SID Flags</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Specified-BSID-Only Flag (S-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Drop-Upon-Invalid Flag (I-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior &amp; SID Structure Flag (B-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3-7</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANASIDFLAGS" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy Segment Flags</name>
        <t>This document creates a new registry called "SR
        Policy Segment Flags" under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel Encapsulation" registry group.
        The registration policy of this registry is "IETF Review" (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The following flags are defined:</t>


<table>
  <name>SR Policy Segment Flags</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Segment Verification Flag (V-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1-2</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>SRv6 Endpoint Behavior &amp; SID Structure Flag (B-Flag)</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4-7</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANAEXTCOMCOFIELD" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Color Extended Community Color-Only Types</name>
        <t>This document creates a new registry called "Color
        Extended Community Color-Only Types" under the "Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Tunnel
        Encapsulation" registry group for assignment of code points (values 0 through
        3) in the Color-Only Type field of the Color Extended Community Flags
        field. The registration policy of this registry is "Standards Action"
        (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>The following types are defined:</t>

<table>
  <name>Color Extended Community Color-Only Types</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Specific Endpoint Match</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Specific or Null Endpoint Match</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>    
      <td>Specific, Null, or Any Endpoint Match</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Unassigned</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
      <section anchor="IANAENLP" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SR Policy ENLP Values</name>
        <t>IANA will maintain a new registry under the
        "Segment Routing" registry group with the registration policy of
        "Standards Action" (see <xref target="RFC8126" format="default"/>). The new registry is
        called "SR Policy ENLP Values" and contains the code points allocated
        to the ENLP field defined in <xref target="ENLPTLV" format="default"/>. The registry
        contains the following code points:</t>

	
<table>
  <name>SR Policy ENLP Values</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Code Point</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>Reserved</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv4 packet but do not push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv6 packet</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv6 packet but do not push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv4 packet</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Push an IPv6 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv6 packet and push an IPv4 Explicit NULL label on an unlabeled IPv4 packet</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>Do not push an Explicit NULL label</td>
      <td>RFC 9830</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5-255</td>
      <td colspan="2">Unassigned</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security mechanisms of the base BGP security model apply to the
      extensions described in this document as well. See the Security
      Considerations section of <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/> for a discussion of
      BGP security. Also, refer to <xref target="RFC4272" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC6952" format="default"/> for analysis of security issues for BGP.</t>

      
      <t>The BGP SR Policy extensions specified in this document enable
      traffic engineering and service programming use cases within an SR
      domain as described in <xref target="RFC9256" format="default"/>. SR operates within a
      trusted SR domain <xref target="RFC8402" format="default"/>; its security
      considerations also apply to BGP sessions when carrying SR Policy
      information. The SR Policies distributed by BGP are expected to be used
      entirely within this trusted SR domain, which comprises a single AS or
      multiple ASes / domains within a single provider network. Therefore,
      precaution is necessary to ensure that the SR Policy information
      advertised via BGP sessions is limited to nodes in a secure manner
      within this trusted SR domain. BGP peering sessions for address families
      other than those that use the SR Policy SAFI may be set up to routers outside the SR
      domain. The isolation of BGP SR Policy SAFI peering sessions may be used
      to ensure that the SR Policy information is not advertised by accident
      or in error to an EBGP peering session outside the SR domain.</t>
      <t>Additionally, it may be a consideration that the export of SR Policy
      information, as described in this document, constitutes a risk to
      confidentiality of mission-critical or commercially sensitive
      information about the network (more specifically endpoint/node
      addresses, SR SIDs, and the SR Policies deployed). BGP peerings are not
      automatic and require configuration; thus, it is the responsibility of
      the network operator to ensure that only trusted nodes (that include
      both routers and controller applications) within the SR domain are
      configured to receive such information.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Manageability" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Manageability Considerations</name>
      <t>The specification of BGP models is an ongoing work based on <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model" format="default"/>; its future extensions are expected
      to cover the SR Policy SAFI. Existing BGP operational procedures also
      apply to the SAFI specified in this document. The management,
      operations, and monitoring of BGP speakers and the SR Policy SAFI
      sessions between them are not very different from other BGP sessions and
      can be managed using the same data models.</t>
      <t>The YANG data model for the operation and management of SR Policies <xref target="I-D.ietf-spring-sr-policy-yang" format="default"/> reports the SR Policies
      provisioned via BGP SR Policy SAFI along with their operational
      states.</t>
    </section>
 
  </middle>
  <back>

    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model" to="BGP-YANG-MODEL"/>
    <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-sr-policy" to="BGP-LS-SR-POLICY"/>
 <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-spring-sr-policy-yang" to="SR-POLICY-YANG"/>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1997.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2545.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5462.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6286.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3032.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9012.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8660.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8754.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9256.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4272.xml"/>


        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model.xml"/>



<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-ls-sr-policy" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ls-sr-policy-17">
   <front>
      <title>Advertisement of Segment Routing Policies using BGP Link-State</title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
         <organization>Individual</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="K." surname="Talaulikar" fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" role="editor">
         <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Dong" fullname="Jie Dong">
         <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="H." surname="Gredler" fullname="Hannes Gredler">
         <organization>RtBrick Inc.</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Tantsura" fullname="Jeff Tantsura">
         <organization>Nvidia</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="March" day="6" year="2025" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ls-sr-policy-17" />
   
</reference>


<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-spring-sr-policy-yang" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-spring-sr-policy-yang-05">
   <front>
      <title>YANG Data Model for Segment Routing Policy</title>
      <author initials="K." surname="Raza" fullname="Syed Kamran Raza" role="editor">
         <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Saleh" fullname="Tarik Saleh">
         <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Z." surname="Shunwan" fullname="Zhuang Shunwan">
         <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Voyer" fullname="Daniel Voyer">
         <organization>Bell Canada</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="M." surname="Durrani" fullname="Muhammad Durrani">
         <organization>Equinix</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="S." surname="Matsushima" fullname="Satoru Matsushima">
         <organization>SoftBank</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="V." surname="Beeram" fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram">
         <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="May" day="25" year="2025" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-spring-sr-policy-yang-05" />
   
</reference>



<reference anchor="RFC9831" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9831">
   <front>
      <title>Segment Type Extensions for BGP Segment Routing (SR) Policy</title>
      <author initials="K." surname="Talaulikar" fullname="Ketan Talaulikar" role="editor">
         <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="C." surname="Filsfils" fullname="Clarence Filsfils">
         <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="S." surname="Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
         <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Mattes" fullname="Paul Mattes">
         <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Jain" fullname="Dhanendra Jain">
         <organization>Google</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="September" year="2025" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9831" />
   <seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC9831'/>
   
</reference>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6952.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9552.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>The authors of this document would like to thank <contact
      fullname="Shyam Sethuram"/>, <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>,
      <contact fullname="Przemyslaw Krol"/>, <contact fullname="Alex
id      Bogdanov"/>, <contact fullname="Nandan Saha"/>, <contact fullname="Bruno
      Decraene"/>, <contact fullname="Gurusiddesh Nidasesi"/>, <contact
      fullname="Kausik Majumdar"/>, <contact fullname="Zafar Ali"/>, <contact
      fullname="Swadesh Agarwal"/>, <contact fullname="Jakob Heitz"/>,
      <contact fullname="Viral Patel"/>, <contact fullname="Peng Shaofu"/>,
      <contact fullname="Cheng Li"/>, <contact fullname="Martin Vigoureux"/>,
      <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>, <contact fullname="Vincent Roca"/>,
      <contact fullname="Brian Haberman"/>, <contact fullname="Mohamed
      Boucadair"/>, <contact fullname="Shunwan Zhuang"/>, <contact
      fullname="Andrew Alston"/>, <contact fullname="Jeffrey (Zhaohui)
      Zhang"/>, <contact fullname="Nagendra Nainar"/>, <contact
      fullname="Rajesh Melarcode Venkateswaran"/>, <contact fullname="Nat
      Kao"/>, <contact fullname="Boris Hassanov"/>, <contact fullname="Vincent
      Roca"/>, <contact fullname="Russ Housley"/>, and <contact fullname="Dan
      Romascanu"/> for their comments and review of this document. The authors
      would like to thank <contact fullname="Susan Hares"/> for her detailed
      shepherd review that helped in improving the document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

    <contact fullname="Eric Rosen">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>erosen@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Arjun Sreekantiah">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>asreekan@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Acee Lindem">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>acee@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Siva Sivabalan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>msiva@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Imtiyaz Mohammad">
      <organization>Arista Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>imtiyaz@arista.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Gaurav Dawra">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>gdawra.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Peng Shaofu">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>peng.shaofu@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Steven Lin">
      <organization>Calix</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>steven.lin@calix.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
