<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
 <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
 <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
 <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]> 

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension-21" number="9894" consensus="true" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DLEP DA Credit Extension">Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Diffserv Aware Credit
    Window Extension</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9894"/>
    <author initials="B." surname="Cheng" fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng">
      <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
          <street>244 Wood Street</street>
          <city>Lexington</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>02421-6426</code>
	  <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bcheng@ll.mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Wiggins" fullname="David Wiggins">
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   <author fullname="Donald E. Eastlake 3rd" initials="D."
           surname="Eastlake 3rd" role="editor">
     <organization>Independent</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>2386 Panoramic Circle</street>
         <city>Apopka</city>
         <region>FL</region>
         <code>32703</code>
         <country>United States of America</country>
       </postal>        
       <phone>+1-508-333-2270</phone>
       <email>d3e3e3@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>
    <date month="January" year="2026"/>
    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>manet</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
  This document defines an extension to the Dynamic Link Exchange
  Protocol (DLEP) that enables a Diffserv aware credit window scheme
  for destination-specific and shared flow control.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec-1" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
  The Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) is defined in <xref
  target="RFC8175"/>.  The protocol provides the exchange of link-related control information between DLEP peers.  DLEP peers consist of
  a modem and a router.  DLEP defines a base set of mechanisms as well
  as support for possible extensions.  This document defines one such
  extension.
      </t>
      <t>
  The DLEP specification does not include any flow control capability.
  Various flow control techniques are theoretically possible with
  DLEP.  This document defines a DLEP extension that provides a
  Diffserv-based flow control mechanism for traffic sent from a router
  to a modem. Flow control is provided using one or more logical "credit
  windows", each of which will typically be supported by an associated
  virtual or physical queue.  A router will use traffic flow
  classification information provided by the modem to identify which
  traffic is associated with each credit window.  Credit windows may be
  shared or dedicated on a per-flow basis.  See <xref
  target="RFC9895"/> for an
  Ethernet-based version of credit window flow control.  As specified in
  <xref section="2.3.1"
  target="RFC9892"/>, when both
  Diffserv and Ethernet traffic classification are specified for a flow,
  the Ethernet information takes precedence.
      </t>
      <t>
  This document uses the traffic classification and credit window flow
  control mechanisms defined in <xref
  target="RFC9892"/> and <xref
  target="RFC9893"/> to provide credit-window-based flow control based on DLEP destinations and Differentiated Services Code Points (DSCPs) <xref target="RFC2475"/>.
  The defined mechanism allows for credit windows to be shared across
  traffic sent to multiple DLEP destinations and DSCPs, or used
  exclusively for traffic sent to a particular destination and/or DSCP.
  The extension also supports the "wildcard" matching of any DSCP.
      </t>
      <t>
  The extension defined in this document is referred to as the "Diffserv
  Aware Credit Window" or, more simply, the "DA Credit" extension. The
  reader should be familiar with both the traffic classification and
  credit window flow control mechanisms defined in <xref
  target="RFC9892"/> and <xref
  target="RFC9893"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
  This document defines a new DLEP Extension Type value
  that is used to indicate support for the
  extension.  See <xref target="sec-ext-type"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="sec-1.1" numbered="true">
        <name>Key Words</name>
         <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document
         are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
         <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
         when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-ext-type" numbered="true">
      <name>Extension Usage and Identification</name>
      <t>
   The extension defined in this document is built on the mechanisms
   and processing defined in <xref
   target="RFC9892"/> and <xref
   target="RFC9893"/>.  To indicate that
   the Diffserv Aware Credit Window Extension is to be used, an
   implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the Diffserv Aware Credit Window Extension Type
   value in the Extensions Supported Data Item (see 
   <xref target="RFC8175" section="13.6"/>).  The Extensions Supported Data Item is
   sent and processed according to <xref target="RFC8175"/>.  Any
   implementation that indicates the use of the Diffserv Aware Credit Window
   Extension <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support all message types, Data Items, the Diffserv Traffic
   Classification Sub-Data Item, and all related processing defined in
   <xref target="RFC9892"/> and <xref
   target="RFC9893"/>.
      </t>


      <t>
  The Diffserv Aware Credit Window Extension Type value is 6. See
  <xref target="sec-iana"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-mgmnt" numbered="true">
      <name>Management Considerations</name>
      <t>
    This section provides several network management guidelines
    for implementations supporting the Diffserv Aware Credit Window
    Extension.
      </t>
      <t>
    If this extension is supported, that support <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be declared
    using the Extensions Supported Data Item (see 
    <xref target="RFC8175" section="13.6"/>). Diffserv Aware Credit Window Extension
    Data Items <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be emitted by a DLEP participant unless such
    support was specified in the initialization message received from
    its peer.  The use of the extension defined in this document
    <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be configurable on both modems and routers. That
    configuration can be implemented using a proprietary Command-Line Interface or by
    implementing a YANG module. The definition of the YANG module is
    out of scope for this document.
      </t>
      <t>
    Modems <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> support the configuration of mapping a DSCP to a credit window (queue).
      </t>
      <t>
    Modems <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> support the configuration of the number of credit
    windows (queues) to advertise to a router.
      </t>
      <t>
    Routers may have limits on the number of queues that they can
    support and limits on supported credit window combinations.
    Per-destination queues might not be supported at all.  When
    credit window information provided by a modem exceeds the capabilities of
    a router, the router <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use a subset of the provided credit
    windows.  Alternatively, a router <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> reset the session and indicate
    that the extension is not supported.  In either case, any mismatch
    in capabilities <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be reported to the user via normal network
    management mechanisms, such as user interface messages or error
    logging.
      </t>
      <t>
    In all cases, if credit windows are in use, traffic for which
    credits are not available <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be sent to the modem by the
    router.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-sec" numbered="true">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
    This document defines a DLEP extension that uses DLEP mechanisms and
    the credit window flow control mechanisms defined in <xref
    target="RFC9892"/> and <xref
    target="RFC9893"/>.  See
    also the Security Considerations sections of those documents.
      </t>
      <t>
    The defined extension is exposed to vulnerabilities similar to
    existing DLEP messages and discussed in the Security Considerations
    section of <xref target="RFC8175"/>, such as an injected message
    resizing a credit window to a value that results in a denial of
    service.  The security mechanisms documented in <xref
    target="RFC8175"/> can be applied equally to the mechanism defined
    in this document.
      </t>
      <t>
    Wildcards for matching Priority Code Point (PCP) and VLAN Identifier (VID)
    fields (see <xref
    target="RFC9895"/>) are provided.  Note that wildcards
    may be convenient for matching a number of packet flows but could
    inadvertently match unexpected flows or new flows that appear after
    the wildcard matching has been set up. It is therefore <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>
    that wildcards not be used unless needed.
      </t>
    </section>
	  
    <section anchor="sec-iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
  IANA has assigned the following code point in the "Extension Type Values"
  registry in the "Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Parameters"
  registry group:
      </t>
        <table anchor="table_et" align="center">
          <name>Extension Type Value</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Code</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">6</td>
              <td align="left">Diffserv Aware Credit Window</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t keepWithPrevious="true"/>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8175.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-manet-dlep-credit-flow-control-19 (RFC 9893) -->
        <reference anchor="RFC9893" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9893">
          <front>
            <title>Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Credit-Based Flow Control Messages and Data Items</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Cheng" fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng">
              <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Wiggins" fullname="David Wiggins">
            </author>
            <author initials="S." surname="Ratliff" fullname="Stan Ratliff">
            </author>
            <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
              <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="E." surname="Kinzie" fullname="Eric Kinzie" role="editor">
              <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="January" year="2026" />
          </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9893"/>
         <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9893"/>
        </reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification-17 (RFC 9892) -->
        <reference anchor="RFC9892" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9892">
          <front>
            <title>Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Traffic Classification Data Item</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Cheng" fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng">
              <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Wiggins" fullname="David Wiggins">
            </author>
            <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
              <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Fedyk" fullname="Don Fedyk" role="editor">
              <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
            </author>
            <date month='January' year='2026'/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9892"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9892"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2475.xml"/>

<!-- draft-ietf-manet-dlep-ether-credit-extension-09 (RFC 9895) -->
<reference anchor="RFC9895" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9895">
   <front>
      <title>Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) IEEE 802.1Q Aware Credit Window Extension</title>
      <author initials="D." surname="Wiggins" fullname="David Wiggins">
         </author>
      <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
         <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake 3rd" fullname="Donald E. Eastlake 3rd" role="editor">
         <organization>Independent</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="January" year="2026" />
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9895"/>
   <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9895"/>   
</reference>

      </references>
    </references>
    <section numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>
     Many useful comments were
     received from contributors to the MANET Working Group, notably
     <contact fullname="Ronald in 't Velt"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
     We had the honor of working too briefly with <contact fullname="David Wiggins"/> on this
     and related DLEP work. His contribution to the IETF and publication
     of the first and definitive open-source DLEP implementation have
     been critical to the acceptance of DLEP. We mourn his passing on
     November 26, 2023.  We wish to recognize his guidance, leadership,
     and professional excellence.  We were fortunate to benefit from his
     leadership and friendship. He shall be missed.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
