<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-lsr-igp-flex-algo-reverse-affinity-12" number="9917" consensus="true" ipr="trust200902" updates="9350, 9843" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Flex-Algorithm Reverse Affinity">IGP Flexible Algorithms Reverse Affinity Constraint</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9917"/>
    <author fullname="Peter Psenak" initials="P." surname="Psenak">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Apollo Business Center</street>
          <street>Mlynske nivy 43</street>
          <city>Bratislava</city>
          <code>82109</code>
          <country>Slovakia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jakub Horn" initials="J." surname="Horn">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Milpitas</city>
          <code>95035</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jakuhorn@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Amit Dhamija" initials="A" surname="Dhamija">
      <organization>Arrcus</organization>
      <address>
        <email>amitd@arrcus.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2026"/>
    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>lsr</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>An IGP Flexible Algorithm (Flex-Algorithm) enables the computation of 
      constraint-based paths within an IGP domain, allowing operators to influence path 
      selection according to administrative policies. This document defines an extension 
      to Flex-Algorithm that allows the inclusion or exclusion of links from path
      computation based on Administrative Groups (also known as link affinities) 
      associated with the reverse direction of the path under computation.</t>
      <t>This document updates RFCs 9350 and 9843
      by introducing the new IANA registry that specifies the ordered set of rules 
      that are used to prune links from the topology during the Flex-Algorithm path 
      computation.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>IGP protocols historically computed the best paths over the network 
      solely based on the IGP metric assigned to the links. An IGP Flex-Algorithm 
      as specified in <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/> allows IGPs to compute constraint-based
      paths. Several mechanisms to include or exclude the link during the Flex-Algorithm 
      path calculation have been defined already:   
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>link inclusion or exclusion based on the presence of a specific
        Admin Group(s) <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/></li>
        <li>link exclusion based on the presence of a specific Shared Risk
        Link Group (SRLG) <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/></li>
        <li>link exclusion based on minimum bandwidth <xref
        target="RFC9843" format="default"/></li>
        <li>link exclusion based on maximum delay <xref
        target="RFC9843" format="default"/></li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document extends IGP Flex-Algorithm with additional constraints
      for inclusion or exclusion of links in the path based on Admin Groups	
	  associated with the reverse direction of the Shortest Path First (SPF) computation.</t>
      <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC9843" format="default"/>
	  by creating the new IANA registry that specifies the ordered set of rules that 
	  are used to prune links from the topology during the Flex-Algorithm path 
	  computation (refer to <xref target="NEW_REG" format="default"/>).</t>
      <t>The term OSPF in this document is used to cover both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3 protocols.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ReqLang" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Use Case Example</name>
      <t>The Flexible Algorithm Definition (FAD) can specify Extended Administrative Groups that are
      used by the operator to include or exclude links during the Flex-Algorithm path
      computation <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/>. These link Extended Administrative Groups are checked
      in the path direction of the SPF computation, e.g., in the direction from the root 
      vertex toward vertices of increasing distance.</t>
      <t>In certain scenarios, it is beneficial to evaluate the Extended Administrative Groups 
      associated with the reverse direction of a link, rather than solely those 
      in the direction of path computation. Consider a point-to-point link represented 
      as a pair of directed edges between two nodes, A and B. When computing a path from
      A to B, issues such as input errors on the link, detectable only at the receiving 
      node B, may be operationally significant. An operator might monitor metrics like 
      Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) errors or other input-related faults at node B and apply thresholds over a 
      defined observation period. If such a threshold is exceeded, node B may locally 
      assign specific Extended Administrative Groups to the link in the direction from 
      B to A.</t>
      <t>To accommodate this operational intent, the Flex-Algorithm can be extended 
      to inspect the Extended Administrative Groups of the reverse-direction edge (from 
      B to A) when evaluating the forward-direction edge (from A to B) during path
      computation. This enables the exclusion of links from the computed topology 
      based on conditions detected at the far end of the link, improving network 
      reliability and policy control.</t>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Deployment Consideration</name>
      <t>Threshold-based setting of the link Extended Administrative Groups must be done 
      with care to avoid excessive flooding and constant Flex-Algorithm path 
      recalculation.</t>
      <t>One possible approach is to use two different thresholds when setting and unsetting 
      the Extended Administrative Group on the link. For example, when setting the 
      Extended Administrative Group on the link based on the percentage of certain incoming 
      errors, higher threshold is used for setting and lower threshold is used for 
      unsetting the Extended Administrative Group on the link.</t>
      <t>Many implementations provide a throttling mechanism that limits the rate at which 
      the Link State PDU (LSP) in case of IS-IS, or Link State Advertisement (LSA) in case of OSPFv2 and OSPFv3, is updated at the 
      originator. Such mechanism is typically not specific to any particular link 
      attribute, but rather considers any change in the LSP or LSA. Application of such 
      throttling mechanism can also be used to avoid frequent changes in the setting of the 
      Extended Administrative Group on a link to affect the stability of the receivers.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ISISFLEXALGEXLTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group (FAERAG) Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the exclude rule that is used during the 
        Flex-Algorithm path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>The IS-IS FAERAG Sub-TLV is a sub-TLV of the IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV. It has the 
        following format: 
      </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Type     |    Length     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Extended Admin Group                     |
+-                                                             -+
|                            ...                                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
<t>where:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Type (1 octet):</dt><dd>10</dd>
        <dt>Length (1 octet):</dt><dd>Variable, dependent on the size of the
        Extended Admin Group. The length <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a multiple of
        4 octets. If the length is not a multiple of 4 octets, the entire
        sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</dd>
        <dt>Extended Administrative Group:</dt><dd>Extended Administrative
        Group as defined in <xref target="RFC7308" format="default"/>.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The IS-IS FAERAG Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in a single IS-IS
        FAD Sub-TLV. If it appears more than once, the IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        be ignored by the receiver.</t>
      <t>The IS-IS FAERAG Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in the set of FAD 
        Sub-TLVs for a given Flex-Algorithm from a given IS. If it appears more than once 
        in such set, the IS-IS FAERAG Sub-TLV in the first occurrence in the lowest-numbered 
        LSP from a given IS <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used and any other occurrences <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored
        by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ISISFLEXALGINCANYTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the include-any rule that is used during the Flex-Algorithm
        path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The format of the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group
        Sub-TLV is identical to the format of the FAERAG Sub-TLV in 
        <xref target="ISISFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>IANA has assigned Type value of 11 for the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any 
        Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV.</t>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> 
        appear more than once in a single IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV. If it appears more than once, 
        the IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</t>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> 
        appear more than once in the set of FAD Sub-TLVs for a given Flex-Algorithm from
        a given IS. If it appears more than once in such set, the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm
        Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV in the first occurrence in the lowest-numbered 
        LSP from a given IS <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used and any other occurrences <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored 
        by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ISISFLEXALGINCALLTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the include-all rule that is used during the Flex-Algorithm
        path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The format of the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group
        Sub-TLV is identical to the format of the FAERAG Sub-TLV in
         <xref target="ISISFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>IANA has assigned Type value of 12 for the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All 
        Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV.</t>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> 
        appear more than once in a single IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV. If it appears more than once, 
        the IS-IS FAD Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</t>
      <t>The IS-IS Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> 
        appear more than once in the set of FAD Sub-TLVs for a given Flex-Algorithm from 
        a given IS. If it appears more than once in such set, the IS-IS Flexible Algorithm 
        Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV in the first occurrence in the lowest-numbered 
        LSP from a given IS <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used and any other occurrences <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored
        by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="OSPFFLEXALGEXLTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>OSPF Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The OSPF Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group (FAERAG) Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the exclude rule that is used during the 
        Flex-Algorithm path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>The OSPF FAERAG Sub-TLV is a sub-TLV of the OSPF FAD TLV. It has the 
        following format: </t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              Type             |             Length            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Extended Admin Group                     |
+-                                                             -+
|                            ...                                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
<t>where:</t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Type (2 octets):</dt><dd>10</dd>
        <dt>Length (2 octets):</dt><dd>Variable, dependent on the size of the
        Extended Admin Group. The length <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a multiple of
        4 octets. If the length is not a multiple of 4 octets, the entire
        sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</dd>
        <dt>Extended Administrative Group:</dt><dd>Extended Administrative
        Group as defined in <xref target="RFC7308" format="default"/>.</dd>
      </dl>
      <t>The OSPF FAERAG Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in an OSPF
        FAD TLV. If it appears more than once, the OSPF FAD TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        ignored by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="OSPFFLEXALGINCANYTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the include-any rule that is used during the Flex-Algorithm
        path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The format of the OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group
        Sub-TLV is identical to the format of the OSPF FAERAG Sub-TLV in <xref target="OSPFFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>IANA has assigned Type value of 11 for the OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-Any 
        Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV.</t>
      <t>The OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST
        NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in an OSPF FAD TLV. If it appears more than
        once, the OSPF FAD TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="OSPFFLEXALGINCALLTLV" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV</name>
      <t>The OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV 
        is used to advertise the include-all rule that is used during the Flex-Algorithm
        path calculation as specified in <xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The format of the OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group
        Sub-TLV is identical to the format of the OSPF FAERAG Sub-TLV in <xref target="OSPFFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>IANA has assigned Type value of 12 for the OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse 
        Admin Group Sub-TLV.</t>
      <t>The OSPF Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group Sub-TLV <bcp14>MUST
        NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in an OSPF FAD TLV. If it appears more than
        once, the OSPF FAD TLV <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored by the receiver.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="FLEXALGPATHCALC" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Calculation of Flexible Algorithm Paths</name>
      <t>The following procedures augment the rules defined in  
       <xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/> by introducing additional constraints based on 
       Administrative Groups (AGs) associated with the reverse direction of a link. 
      </t>  
      <ul spacing="normal" >
        <li>Check if any exclude reverse Admin Group rule is part of the
        Flex-Algorithm definition. If such exclude rule exists, check if any
        Admin Group that is part of the exclude rule is also set on the link
        in the reverse direction.  If such Admin Group is set on the link in
        the reverse direction, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the
        computation.</li>
        <li>Check if any include-any reverse Admin Group rule is part of the
        Flex-Algorithm definition. If such include-any rule exists, check if
        any Admin Group that is part of the include-any rule is also set on
        the link in the reverse direction. If no such Admin Group is set on
        the link in the reverse direction, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        pruned from the computation.</li>
        <li>Check if any include-all reverse Admin Group rule is part of the
        Flex-Algorithm definition. If such include-all rule exists, check if
        all Admin Groups that are part of the include-all rule are also set on
        the link in the reverse direction. If all such Admin Groups are not
        set on the link in the reverse direction, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        be pruned from the computation.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>Please see rules 8, 9, and 10 in <xref target="PATHCOMPREGISTRY" format="default"/> for these added 
        rules.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="SUBTLVREGISTRY" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Sub-Sub-TLVs for Flexible Algorithm Definition Sub-TLV</name>
        <t>IANA has registered the following in the 
          "IS-IS Sub-Sub-TLVs for Flexible Algorithm Definition Sub-TLV" registry 
          under the "IS-IS TLV Codepoints" registry group:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>10</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>MP:</dt><dd>n</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="ISISFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>11</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>MP:</dt><dd>n</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="ISISFLEXALGINCANYTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>12</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>MP:</dt><dd>n</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="ISISFLEXALGINCALLTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>OSPF Flexible Algorithm Definition TLV Sub-TLV Registry</name>
        <t>This document makes the following registration in the "OSPF Flexible
           Algorithm Definition TLV Sub-TLVs" registry under the "Open Shortest 
           Path First (OSPF) Parameters" registry group:
        </t>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>10</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Exclude Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="OSPFFLEXALGEXLTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>11</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Include-Any Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="OSPFFLEXALGINCANYTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
        <dl newline="false" spacing="compact">
          <dt>Type:</dt><dd>12</dd>
          <dt>Description:</dt><dd>Flexible Algorithm Include-All Reverse Admin Group</dd>
          <dt>Reference:</dt><dd>RFC 9917, <xref target="OSPFFLEXALGINCALLTLV" format="default"/></dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="PATHCOMPREGISTRY" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Computation Rules Registry</name>
        <t>IANA has created a new registry called "IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Computation 
          Rules" within the "Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) Parameters" 
          registry group. The registration procedure for the new registry is 
          Expert Review <xref target="RFC8126"/>. <xref target="NEW_REG" format="default"/> provides guidance for designated experts.</t>
        <t>The "IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Computation Rules" registry specifies the ordered 
          set of rules that are used to prune links from the topology during 
          the Flex-Algorithm path computation.</t>
        <t>There is no upper bound on the number of rules that the registry supports.</t>
  <t>In <xref target="flex-algo-rules"/>, "FAEMB" means "Flex-Algorithm Exclude Minimum Bandwidth",
   and "FAEMD" means "Flex-Algorithm Exclude Maximum Delay".</t>
        <table align="center" anchor="flex-algo-rules">
          <name>IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Calculation Rules</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Sequence Number</th>
              <th>Description</th>
              <th>Reference</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>Check if any exclude 
                Administrative Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm Definition. 
                If such exclude rule exists, check if any color that is part of the 
                exclude rule is also set on the link. If such a color is set, 
                the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>Check if any exclude SRLG rule 
                is part of the Flex-Algorithm Definition. If such exclude rule exists, 
                check if the link is part of any SRLG that is also part of the 
                SRLG exclude rule. If the link is part of such SRLG, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> 
                be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>Check if any include-any 
                Administrative Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm Definition. If 
                such include-any rule exists, check if any color that is part of the 
                include-any rule is also set on the link. If no such color is set, 
                the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>Check if any include-all 
                Administrative Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm Definition. 
                If such include-all rule exists, check if all colors that are part 
                of the include-all rule are also set on the link. If all such colors 
                are not set on the link, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>If the Flex-Algorithm Definition 
                uses something other than the IGP metric (<xref target="RFC9350" section="5"/>), 
                and such metric is not advertised for the particular link in a topology for 
                which the computation is done, such link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation. 
                A metric of value 0 <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be assumed in such a case.</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC9350" section="13"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>6</td>
              <td> Check if any exclude FAEMB 
                rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm definition. If such exclude rule
                 exists and the link has Maximum Link Bandwidth advertised, check if the 
                link bandwidth satisfies the FAEMB rule. If the link does not satisfy the 
                FAEMB rule, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the Flex-Algorithm computation.</td>
              <td><xref section="6" target="RFC9843"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>7</td>
              <td>Check if any exclude FAEMD rule 
                is part of the Flex-Algorithm definition. If such exclude rule exists 
                and the link has Min Unidirectional link delay advertised, check if the 
                link delay satisfies the FAEMD rule. If the link does not satisfy the 
                FAEMD rule, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the Flex-Algorithm computation.</td>
              <td><xref section="6" target="RFC9843"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>8</td>
              <td>Check if any exclude 
                reverse Admin Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm
                definition. If such exclude rule exists, check if any Admin Group that is
                part of the exclude rule is also set on the link in the reverse direction. 
                If such Admin Group is set on the link in the reverse direction, the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> 
                be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC"/> of RFC 9917</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>9</td>
              <td>Check if any include-any 
                reverse Admin Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm
                definition. If such include-any rule exists, check if any Admin Group that
                is part of the include-any rule is also set on the link in the reverse 
                direction. If no such Admin Group is set on the link in the reverse direction, 
                the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC"/> of RFC 9917</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>10</td>
              <td>Check if any include-all 
                reverse Admin Group rule is part of the Flex-Algorithm
                definition. If such include-all rule exists, check if all Admin Groups
                that are part of the include-all rule are also set on the link in the reverse
                direction. If all such Admin Groups are not set on the link in the reverse direction,
                the link <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be pruned from the computation.</td>
              <td><xref target="FLEXALGPATHCALC"/> of RFC 9917</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
    <section anchor="NEW_REG" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Guidance for Designated Experts</name>
      <t>Since the original Flex-Algorithm specification <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/>, many 
      Flex-Algorithm extensions have been proposed and standardized. Many of them added 
      additional rules to the Flex-Algorithm path computation. Maintaining an IANA registry 
      for these rules allows specification across multiple documents progressing 
      independently. The new "IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Computation Rules" registry has been
      created and is specified in <xref target="PATHCOMPREGISTRY" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>This section provides the guidance for designated experts on evaluating new registrations
       in the "IGP Flex-Algorithm Path Computation Rules" registry:</t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
       <li>
          When a new constraint is defined, the rule associated with that constraint 
       <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be inserted at any position. Backwards compatibility is guaranteed because 
       nodes that don't support the new constraint will not participate in an 
       algorithm where the FAD specifies a constraint they don't support.
        </li>
        <li>
          The relative ordering of existing rules <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be altered. Doing so has 
           the potential to create backwards compatibility issues.
        </li>
        <li>
          Deletion of the rules <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be done. Given that the rules are only used
      conditionally based on the information carried in the winning FAD, deletion of 
      the rule is not necessary.
        </li>
        <li>
          Merging or repeating of the rules <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be done.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>	
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document inherits security considerations from <xref target="RFC9350" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7308.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9350.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9843.xml"/>
    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
    </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
