<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-roll-aodv-rpl-20" number="9854" updates="" obsoletes="" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="4" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3" xml:lang="en">

<front>
    <title abbrev="AODV-RPL">AODV-RPL: The Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks (RPL)
     Based on Ad Hoc On-Demand Distance Vector (AODV) Routing</title>
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9854"/>
    <author fullname="Charles E. Perkins" initials="C.E." surname="Perkins">
      <organization>Blue Meadow Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Saratoga</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95070</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>
        <email>charliep@lupinlodge.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="S.V.R. Anand" initials="S.V.R." surname="Anand">
      <organization>Indian Institute of Science</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <code>560012</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>anandsvr@iisc.ac.in</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Satish Anamalamudi" initials="S." surname="Anamalamudi">
      <organization>SRM University-AP</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Amaravati Campus</street>
          <city>Amaravati, Andhra Pradesh</city>
          <code>522 502</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>satishnaidu80@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Bing Liu" initials="B." surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>
	  <cityarea>Haidian District</cityarea>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>remy.liubing@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2025" month="October"/>

    <area>RTG</area>
    <workgroup>roll</workgroup>

    <keyword>AODV</keyword>
    <keyword>Peer-to-Peer Route Discovery</keyword>
    <keyword>Asymmetric</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Route discovery for symmetric and asymmetric Peer-to-Peer (P2P)
      traffic flows is a desirable feature in Low-Power and Lossy Networks
      (LLNs).  For that purpose, this document specifies AODV-RPL -- the
      Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks (RPL) based on Ad hoc
      On-demand Distance Vector (AODV) routing. AODV-RPL is a reactive P2P
      route discovery mechanism for both hop-by-hop routes and source
      routing.  Paired instances are used to construct directional paths for
      cases where there are asymmetric links between source and target nodes.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        The Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks (RPL)
        <xref target="RFC6550"/> is an IPv6 distance vector routing protocol
	designed to support multiple traffic flows through a root-based
	Destination-Oriented Directed Acyclic Graph (DODAG). Typically,
	a router does not have routing information for destinations attached
        to most other routers.  Consequently, for traffic
        between routers within the DODAG (i.e., P2P traffic),
        data packets either have to traverse the root in non-storing mode or
        traverse a common ancestor in storing mode.  Such P2P traffic
        is thereby likely to traverse longer routes and
        may suffer severe congestion near the root (for more information,
        see <xref target="RFC6687"/>, <xref target="RFC6997"/>,
        <xref target="RFC6998"/>, and <xref target="RFC9010"/>).
        The network environment that is considered in this document
        is assumed to be the same as that described in 
        <xref target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="of" section="1"/>.
        Each radio interface/link and the associated address should be
        treated as an independent intermediate router.  Such routers
        have different links, and the rules for link symmetry
        apply independently for each of these.

      </t>
      <t>
        The route discovery process in AODV-RPL is modeled on the analogous
        P2P procedure specified in AODV <xref target="RFC3561"/>.
	The on-demand property of AODV route discovery is useful for the needs
        of routing in RPL-based LLNs when routes are needed but aren't yet
        established.  P2P routing is desirable to discover
        shorter routes, especially when it is desired to avoid directing
        additional traffic through a root or gateway node of the network.
        It may happen that some routes need to be established proactively
        when known beforehand and when AODV-RPL's route discovery process
        introduces unwanted delay when the application is
        launched.
      </t>
      <t>
        AODV terminology has been adapted for use with AODV-RPL messages,
        namely "RREQ" for "Route Request", and "RREP" for "Route Reply".
        AODV-RPL currently omits some features compared to AODV -- in
        particular, flagging route errors, blocking the use of unidirectional links
        <xref target="RFC3561"/>, multihoming, and handling unnumbered
        interfaces.
      </t>
      <t>AODV-RPL reuses and extends the core RPL functionality to support
      routes with bidirectional asymmetric links.  It retains RPL's DODAG
      formation, RPL Instance and the associated Objective Function (OF) (defined
      in <xref target="RFC6551"/>), Trickle timers, and support for storing
      and non-storing modes.  AODV-RPL adds the basic messages RREQ and RREP as
      part of the RPL DODAG Information Object (DIO) control message, which go in
      separate (paired) RPL Instances.  AODV-RPL does not utilize the
      Destination Advertisement Object (DAO) control message of RPL.
        AODV-RPL uses the "P2P Route Discovery Mode of Operation" (MOP == 4)
        with three new options for the DIO message, dedicated to discovering
        P2P routes. These P2P routes may differ from routes discoverable by
        RPL <xref target="RFC6550"/>.  Since AODV-RPL uses newly defined options and a newly
        allocated multicast group (see <xref target="iana"/>), there is no
        conflict with P2P-RPL <xref target="RFC6997"/>, a previous document
        using the same MOP.  AODV-RPL can be operated whether or not P2P-RPL
        or RPL <xref target="RFC6550"/> is also running.  AODV-RPL could be used for networks in
        which routes are needed with OFs that cannot be
        satisfied by routes that are constrained to traverse the root of the
        network or other common ancestors.  P2P routes often require fewer
        hops and therefore consume less resources than routes that traverse
        the root or other common ancestors.  Similar in cost to base RPL <xref
        target="RFC6550"/>, the cost will depend on many
        factors such as the proximity of the OrigNode and TargNodes and
        distribution of symmetric/asymmetric P2P links.  Experience with
        AODV <xref target="aodv-tot"/> suggests that AODV-RPL will often find
        routes with improved Rank compared to routes constrained to traverse
        a common ancestor of the source and destination nodes.
      </t>
    </section>

<section anchor="terms">
      <name>Terminology</name>
              <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref
    target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
    shown here.
        </t>
	<t>
          AODV-RPL reuses names for messages and data structures, including
          Rank, DODAG, and DODAGID, as defined in RPL <xref
          target="RFC6550"/>.
	</t>
	
	<t>This document also uses the following terms:</t>
	<dl newline="true" spacing="normal">

        <dt>AODV</dt>
        <dd>Ad hoc On-Demand Distance Vector <xref target="RFC3561"/>.</dd>
        <dt>ART option</dt>
        <dd>The AODV-RPL Target option defined in this document.</dd>

        <dt>Asymmetric route</dt>
        <dd>The route from the OrigNode to the TargNode can traverse different
        nodes than the route from the TargNode to the OrigNode. An asymmetric
        route may result from the asymmetry of links, such that only one
        direction of the series of links satisfies the OF
        during route discovery.</dd>
        <dt>Bidirectional asymmetric link</dt>
        <dd>A link that can be used in both directions but with different link
        characteristics.</dd>

        <dt>DIO</dt>
        <dd>DODAG Information Object (as defined in <xref target="RFC6550"/>).</dd>

        <dt>DODAG RREQ-Instance (or simply RREQ-Instance)</dt>
        <dd>A RPL Instance built using the DIO with RREQ option; used for
        transmission of control messages from OrigNode to TargNode, thus
        enabling data transmission from TargNode to OrigNode.</dd>

        <dt>DODAG RREP-Instance (or simply RREP-Instance)</dt>
        <dd>A RPL Instance built using the DIO with RREP option; used for
        transmission of control messages from TargNode to OrigNode, thus
        enabling data transmission from OrigNode to TargNode. </dd>

        <dt>Downward direction</dt>
        <dd>The direction from the OrigNode to the TargNode.</dd>

        <dt>Downward route</dt>
        <dd>A route in the downward direction.</dd>

        <dt>Hop-by-hop route</dt>
        <dd>A route for which each router along the routing path stores
        routing information about the next hop. A hop-by-hop route is
        created using RPL's "storing mode".</dd>

        <dt>OF</dt>
        <dd>Objective Function (as defined in <xref target="RFC6550"/>).</dd>

        <dt>OrigNode</dt>
        <dd>The IPv6 router (originating node) initiating the AODV-RPL
        route discovery to obtain a route to TargNode. </dd>

        <dt>Paired DODAGs</dt>
        <dd>Two DODAGs for a single route discovery process between OrigNode
        and TargNode.</dd>

        <dt>P2P</dt>
        <dd>Peer-to-Peer (in other words, not constrained a priori to
        traverse a common ancestor).</dd>

        <dt>REJOIN_REENABLE</dt>
        <dd>The duration during which a node is prohibited from joining a
        DODAG with a particular RREQ-InstanceID, after it has left a DODAG
        with the same RREQ-InstanceID. The default value of REJOIN_REENABLE is
        15 minutes.</dd>

        <dt>RREQ</dt>
        <dd>Route Request.</dd>

        <dt>RREQ-DIO message</dt>
        <dd>A DIO message containing the RREQ option.  The RPLInstanceID in
        RREQ-DIO is assigned locally by the OrigNode.  The RREQ-DIO message
        has a secure variant as noted in <xref target="RFC6550"/>.</dd>

        <dt>RREQ-InstanceID</dt>
        <dd>The RPLInstanceID for the RREQ-Instance. The RREQ-InstanceID is formed
        as the ordered pair (Orig_RPLInstanceID, OrigNode-IPaddr), where
        Orig_RPLInstanceID is the local RPLInstanceID allocated by OrigNode
        and OrigNode-IPaddr is an IP address of OrigNode.  The RREQ-InstanceID
        uniquely identifies the RREQ-Instance.  </dd>

        <dt>RREP</dt>
        <dd>Route Reply.</dd>

        <dt>RREP-DIO message</dt>
        <dd>A DIO message containing the RREP option.  OrigNode pairs the
        RPLInstanceID in RREP-DIO to the one in the associated RREQ-DIO
        message (i.e., the RREQ-InstanceID) as described in <xref
        target="asymmetricrrep"/>. The RREP-DIO message has a secure variant
        as noted in <xref target="RFC6550"/>.</dd>

        <dt>RREP-InstanceID</dt>
        <dd>
        The RPLInstanceID for the RREP-Instance.  The RREP-InstanceID is formed
        as the ordered pair (Targ_RPLInstanceID, TargNode-IPaddr), where
        Targ_RPLInstanceID is the local RPLInstanceID allocated by TargNode
        and TargNode-IPaddr is an IP address of TargNode.  The RREP-InstanceID
        uniquely identifies the RREP-Instance.  The RPLInstanceID in the RREP
        message along with the Delta value indicates the associated
        RREQ-InstanceID.  The InstanceIDs are matched by the mechanism explained
        in <xref target="instancepairing"/>.</dd>

        <dt>Source routing</dt>
        <dd>A mechanism by which the source supplies a vector of addresses
        towards the destination node along with each data packet <xref
        target="RFC6550"/>.</dd>

        <dt>Symmetric route</dt>
        <dd>The upstream and downstream routes traverse the same routers and over
        the same links.</dd>

	<dt>TargNode</dt>
        <dd>The IPv6 router (target node) for which OrigNode requires a
        route and initiates route discovery within the LLN. </dd>

	<dt>Upward direction</dt>
        <dd>The direction from the TargNode to the OrigNode.</dd>

        <dt>Upward route</dt>
        <dd>A route in the upward direction.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Overview of AODV-RPL</name>
      <t>
        With AODV-RPL, routes from OrigNode to TargNode within the LLN
        do not become established until they are needed.  The route
        discovery mechanism in AODV-RPL is invoked when OrigNode
        has data for delivery to a TargNode, but existing routes do not
        satisfy the application's requirements.  For this reason,
        AODV-RPL is considered to be an example of an "on-demand" routing
        protocol.  Such protocols are also known as "reactive" routing
        protocols since their operations are triggered in reaction to
        a determination that a new route is needed.

        AODV-RPL works
        without requiring the use of RPL or any other routing protocol.
      </t>
      <t>
        The routes discovered by
        AODV-RPL are not constrained to traverse a common ancestor.
        AODV-RPL can enable asymmetric communication paths in networks with
        bidirectional asymmetric links. For this purpose, AODV-RPL enables
        discovery of two routes: namely, one from OrigNode to TargNode and
        another from TargNode to OrigNode.  AODV-RPL also
        enables discovery of symmetric routes along paired DODAGs, when
        symmetric routes are possible (see <xref target="channel"/>).
      </t>
      <t>
        In AODV-RPL, routes are discovered by first forming a temporary
        Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) rooted at the OrigNode.  Paired DODAGs
        (Instances) are constructed during route formation between the
        OrigNode and TargNode.  The RREQ-Instance is formed by route control
        messages from OrigNode to TargNode, whereas the RREP-Instance is
        formed by route control messages from TargNode to OrigNode.  The route
        discovered in the RREQ-Instance is used for transmitting data from
        TargNode to OrigNode, and the route discovered in RREP-Instance is
        used for transmitting data from OrigNode to TargNode.
      </t>
      <t>
        Intermediate routers join the DODAGs based on the Rank
        <xref target="RFC6550"/> as calculated from the DIO messages.
        AODV-RPL uses the same notion of Rank as
        defined in <xref target="RFC6550"/>:</t>

	<blockquote>The Rank is the expression of a relative position within
	a DODAG Version with regard to neighbors, and it is not necessarily a
	good indication or a proper expression of a distance or a path cost to
	the root.</blockquote>

	<t>The Rank measurements provided in AODV messages do not indicate a
	distance or a path cost to the root.
      </t>
      <t>
        Henceforth in this document, "RREQ-DIO message" means the DIO
	message from OrigNode toward TargNode, containing the RREQ option as
	specified in <xref target="RREQmsg"/>.  The RREQ-InstanceID is formed
	as the ordered pair (Orig_RPLInstanceID, OrigNode-IPaddr), where
	Orig_RPLInstanceID is the local RPLInstanceID allocated by OrigNode
	and OrigNode-IPaddr is the IP address of OrigNode.  A node receiving
	the RREQ-DIO can use the RREQ-InstanceID to identify the proper OF
	whenever that node receives a data packet with Source Address ==
	OrigNode-IPaddr and IPv6 RPL Option having the RPLInstanceID ==
	Orig_RPLInstanceID.  The D bit of the RPLInstanceID field is set
        to 0 to indicate that the source address of the IPv6 packet is
        the DODAGID.
      </t>
      <t>
	Similarly, "RREP-DIO message" means the DIO message from TargNode
	toward OrigNode, containing the RREP option as specified in
	<xref target="RREPmsg"/>.  The RREP-InstanceID is formed
	as the ordered pair (Targ_RPLInstanceID, TargNode-IPaddr), where
	Targ_RPLInstanceID is the local RPLInstanceID allocated by TargNode
	and TargNode-IPaddr is the IP address of TargNode.  A node receiving
	the RREP-DIO can use the RREP-InstanceID to identify the proper OF
	whenever that node receives a data packet with Source Address ==
	TargNode-IPaddr and IPv6 RPL Option having the RPLInstanceID ==
	Targ_RPLInstanceID along with D == 0 as above.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Options">
      <name>AODV-RPL DIO Options</name>
      <section anchor="RREQmsg">
        <name>AODV-RPL RREQ Option</name>
        <t>
	OrigNode selects one of its IPv6 addresses and sets it in the DODAGID
	field of the RREQ-DIO message.  The address scope of the selected
	address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> encompass the domain where the route is built (e.g, not
	link-local); otherwise, the route discovery will fail.  Exactly one
        RREQ option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present
	in an RREQ-DIO message; otherwise, the message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be dropped.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figRREQ">
          <name>Format for AODV-RPL RREQ Option</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  Option Type  | Option Length |S|H|X| Compr | L |  RankLimit  |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  Orig SeqNo   |                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               |
    |                                                               |
    |           Address Vector (Optional, Variable Length)          |
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ . . .]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>OrigNode supplies the following information in the RREQ option: </t>

        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Option Type</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the type of the option (0x0B).</dd>
	  
          <dt>Option Length</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the length of the option in
          octets, excluding the Option Type and Option Length fields.  It is
          variable due to the presence of the Address Vector and the number of
          octets elided according to the Compr value.</dd>

          <dt>S</dt>
          <dd>Symmetric bit indicating a symmetric route from the OrigNode to
          the router transmitting this RREQ-DIO. See <xref
          target="channel"/>.</dd>

          <dt>H</dt>
          <dd>Set to one for a hop-by-hop route.  Set to zero for a source
          route.  This flag controls both the downstream route and upstream
          route.</dd>

          <dt>X</dt>
          <dd>Reserved. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be initialized to zero and ignored
          upon reception.</dd>

          <dt>Compr</dt>
          <dd>4-bit unsigned integer. When Compr is nonzero, exactly that
          number of prefix octets <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be elided from each
          address before storing it in the Address Vector. The octets elided
          are shared with the IPv6 address in the DODAGID. This field is only
          used in source routing mode (H=0).  In hop-by-hop mode (H=1), this
          field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero and ignored upon
          reception.</dd>
	  <dt>L</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>2-bit unsigned integer determining the time duration that a
            node is able to belong to the RREQ-Instance (a temporary DAG
            including the OrigNode and the TargNode).  Once the time is
            reached, a node <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> leave the RREQ-Instance and
            stop sending or receiving any more DIOs for the RREQ-Instance;
            otherwise, memory and network resources are likely to be consumed
            unnecessarily.  This naturally depends on the node's ability to
            keep track of time.  Once a node leaves an RREQ-Instance, it
            <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> rejoin the same RREQ-Instance for at least
            the time interval specified by the configuration variable
            REJOIN_REENABLE. L is independent from the route lifetime, which
            is defined in the DODAG configuration option.
            </t>
            <ul spacing="compact">
              <li>
                <t>0x00: No time limit imposed</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>0x01: 16 seconds</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>0x02: 64 seconds</t>
              </li>
              <li>
                <t>0x03: 256 seconds</t>
              </li>
            </ul>
            <t>
            </t>
          </dd>
          <dt>RankLimit</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the upper limit on the integer
          portion of the Rank (calculated using the DAGRank() macro defined in
          <xref target="RFC6550"/>).  A value of 0 in this field indicates the
          limit is infinity.</dd>
          <dt>Orig SeqNo</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the Sequence Number of
          OrigNode.  See <xref target="rreq"/>.</dd>
          <dt>Address Vector</dt>
          <dd>A vector of IPv6 addresses representing the route that the
          RREQ-DIO has passed. It is only present when the H bit is set to 0.
          The prefix of each address is elided according to the Compr
          field.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>TargNode can join the RREQ-Instance at a Rank whose integer portion is
	less than or equal to the RankLimit.  Any other node <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> join an
	RREQ-Instance if its own Rank would be equal to or higher than the
	RankLimit.  A router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard a received RREQ if the integer part
	of the advertised Rank equals or exceeds the RankLimit.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="RREPmsg">
        <name>AODV-RPL RREP Option</name>
        <t>
	TargNode sets one of its IPv6 addresses in the DODAGID
	field of the RREP-DIO message.  The address scope of the selected
	address must encompass the domain where the route is built (e.g, not
	link-local).   Exactly one RREP option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be present
	in an RREP-DIO message, otherwise, the message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be dropped.
	TargNode supplies the following information in the RREP option:
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figRREP">
          <name>Format for AODV-RPL RREP Option</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Option Type  | Option Length |G|H|X| Compr | L |  RankLimit  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   Delta   |X X|                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               |
   |                                                               |
   |                                                               |
   |           Address Vector (Optional, Variable Length)          |
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ . . .]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Option Type</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the type of the option (0x0C).</dd>

          <dt>Option Length</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the length of the option in
          octets, excluding the Option Type and Option Length fields.  It is
          variable due to the presence of the Address Vector and the number of
          octets elided according to the Compr value.</dd>

          <dt>G</dt>
          <dd>Gratuitous RREP (see <xref target="G-RREP"/>).</dd>

          <dt>H</dt>
          <dd>The H bit in the RREP option <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to be
          the same as the H bit in the RREQ option.  It requests either source
          routing (H=0) or hop-by-hop (H=1) for the downstream route.</dd>

          <dt>X</dt>
          <dd>1-bit Reserved field. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be initialized to zero
          and ignored upon reception.</dd>

          <dt>Compr</dt>
          <dd>4-bit unsigned integer. This field has the same definition as in the RREQ option.</dd>

          <dt>L</dt>
          <dd>2-bit unsigned integer defined as in the RREQ option.  The lifetime
          of the RREP-Instance <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be no greater than the
          lifetime of the RREQ-Instance to which it is paired, so that the
          memory required to store the RREP-Instance can be reclaimed when no
          longer needed.</dd>

          <dt>RankLimit</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the upper limit on the integer
          portion of the Rank, similarly to RankLimit in the RREQ message.  A
          value of 0 in this field indicates the limit is infinity.</dd>

	  <dt>Delta</dt>
          <dd>6-bit unsigned integer. TargNode uses the Delta field so that
          nodes receiving its RREP message can identify the RREQ-InstanceID of
          the RREQ message that triggered the transmission of the RREP (see
          <xref target="instancepairing"/>).</dd>

          <dt>X X</dt>
          <dd>2-bit Reserved field. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be initialized to zero
          and ignored upon reception.</dd>
          <dt>Address Vector</dt>
          <dd>
	    Only present when the H bit is set to 0. The prefix of each address
	    is elided according to the Compr field.  For an asymmetric route,
	    the Address Vector represents the IPv6 addresses of the path
	    through the network the RREP-DIO has passed.  In contrast, for a
	    symmetric route, it is the Address Vector when the RREQ-DIO arrives
	    at the TargNode, unchanged during the transmission to the OrigNode.
	    </dd>
        </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="artop">
        <name>AODV-RPL Target Option</name>
        <t> The AODV-RPL Target (ART) option is based on the Target option
	in the core RPL specification <xref target="RFC6550"/>.  The Flags field is replaced by
	the Destination Sequence Number of the TargNode, and the Prefix
	Length field is reduced to 7 bits so that the value is limited to
	be no greater than 127.  </t>
        <t>
	An RREQ-DIO message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> carry at least one ART option.  An RREP-DIO
	message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> carry exactly one ART option. Otherwise, the message
	<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be dropped.
        </t>
        <t>
	OrigNode can include multiple TargNode addresses via multiple ART
	options in the RREQ-DIO, for routes that share the same requirement on
	metrics.  This reduces the cost to building only one DODAG for
	multiple targets.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figTarg">
          <name>ART Option Format for AODV-RPL</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Option Type  | Option Length |  Dest SeqNo   |X|Prefix Length|
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               |
   |           Target Prefix / Address (Variable Length)           |
   .                                                               .
   .                                                               .
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ . . .]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Option Type</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the type of the option (0x0D).</dd>

          <dt>Option Length</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer specifying the length of the option in
          octets, excluding the Option Type and Option Length fields.</dd>

          <dt>Dest SeqNo</dt>
          <dd>8-bit unsigned integer. In RREQ-DIO, if nonzero, it is the
          Sequence Number for the last route that OrigNode stored to the
          TargNode for which a route is desired.  In RREP-DIO, it is the
          Destination Sequence Number associated to the route.  Zero is used
          if there is no known information about the Sequence Number of
          TargNode and not used otherwise.</dd>

          <dt>X</dt>
          <dd>1-bit Reserved field.  This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
          initialized to zero by the sender and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored
          by the receiver.</dd>

          <dt>Prefix Length</dt>
          <dd>7-bit unsigned integer.  The Prefix Length field contains the
          number of valid leading bits in the prefix. If Prefix Length is 0,
          then the value in the Target Prefix / Address field represents an
          IPv6 address, not a prefix.</dd>

          <dt>Target Prefix / Address</dt>
          <dd>A variable-length field with an IPv6 destination address or prefix.
          The length of the Target Prefix / Address field is the least number
          of octets that can represent all of the bits of the Prefix, in other
          words, Ceil(Prefix Length/8) octets.  When Prefix Length is not equal
          to 8*Ceil(Prefix Length/8) and nonzero, the Target Prefix / Address
          field will contain some initial bits that are not part of the Target
          Prefix.  Those initial bits (if any) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
          zero on transmission and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be ignored on receipt.
          If Prefix Length is zero, the Address field is 128 bits.
	</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="channel">
      <name>Symmetric and Asymmetric Routes</name>
      <t>
	Links are considered symmetric until indication to the contrary is
	received.  In Figures <xref target="figSymm-a" format="counter"/> and
	<xref target="figSymm-b" format="counter"/>, BR is the Border Router, O is the
	OrigNode, each R is an intermediate router, and T is the TargNode.
	In these examples, the use of BR is only for illustrative purposes;
	AODV does not depend on the use of border routers for its operation.
	If the RREQ-DIO arrives over an interface that
	is known to be symmetric and the S bit is set to 1, then it remains
	as 1, as illustrated in <xref target="figSymm-a"/>.  If an
	intermediate router sends out RREQ-DIO with the S bit set to 1, then
	each link en route from the OrigNode O to this router has met
	the requirements of route discovery, and the route can be used
	symmetrically.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figSymm-a">
        <name>AODV-RPL with Symmetric Instances</name>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                               BR
                           /----+----\
                         /      |      \
                       /        |         \
                      R         R           R
                   _/  \        |          /  \
                  /     \       |         /     \
                 /       \      |        /        \
               R -------- R --- R ----- R -------- R
             /  \   <--S=1-->  / \    <--S=1-->   /  \
      <--S=1-->  \            /   \             /   <--S=1-->
        /         \          /     \          /         \
      O ---------- R ------ R------ R ----- R ----------- T
     / \                   / \             / \           / \
    /   \                 /   \           /   \         /   \
   /     \               /     \         /     \       /     \
  R ----- R ----------- R ----- R ----- R ----- R ---- R----- R

    >---- RREQ-Instance (Control: O-->T;  Data: T-->O) ------->
    <---- RREP-Instance (Control: T-->O;  Data: O-->T) -------< ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
	Upon receiving an RREQ-DIO with the S bit set to 1, a node determines
	whether the link over which it was received can be used symmetrically,
	i.e., both directions meet the requirements of data transmission.  If
	the RREQ-DIO arrives over an interface that is not known to be
	symmetric or is known to be asymmetric, the S bit is set to 0.  If
	the S bit arrives already set to be 0, then it is set to be 0 when the
	RREQ-DIO is propagated (<xref target="figSymm-b"/>).  For an
	asymmetric route, there is at least one hop that doesn't satisfy the
	OF.  Based on the S bit received in RREQ-DIO, TargNode
	T determines whether or not the route is symmetric before transmitting
	the RREP-DIO message upstream towards the OrigNode O.
      </t>
      <t>


	It is beyond the scope of this document to specify the criteria used
	when determining whether or not each link is symmetric.  As an
	example, intermediate routers can use local information (e.g., bit
	rate, bandwidth, number of cells used in 6TiSCH <xref
	target="RFC9030"/>), a priori knowledge (e.g., link quality according
	to previous communication), or averaging techniques as appropriate
	to the application.  Other link metric information can be acquired
	before AODV-RPL operation, by executing evaluation procedures; for
	instance, test traffic can be generated between nodes of the deployed
	network.  During AODV-RPL operation, Operations, Administration, and
	Maintenance (OAM) techniques for evaluating link state (see <xref
	target="RFC7548"/>, <xref target="RFC7276"/>, and <xref
	target="co-ioam"/>) <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used (at regular intervals
	appropriate for the LLN).  The evaluation procedures are out of scope
	for AODV-RPL.  For further information on this topic, see <xref
	target="Link_Asymmetry"/>, <xref target="low-power-wireless"/>, and
	<xref target="empirical-study"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
	<xref target="appendix-a"/> describes an example method using the
	upstream Expected Transmission Count (ETX) and downstream Received
	Signal Strength Indicator (RSSI) to estimate whether the link is
	symmetric in terms of link quality using an averaging technique.

      </t>
      <figure anchor="figSymm-b">
        <name>AODV-RPL with Asymmetric Paired Instances</name>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                                  BR
                              /----+----\
                            /      |      \
                          /        |        \
                        R          R          R
                      / \          |        /   \
                    /     \        |       /      \
                  /         \      |      /         \
                 R --------- R --- R ---- R --------- R
               /  \   --S=1-->   / \    --S=0-->   /   \
         --S=1-->   \           /    \            /   --S=0-->
          /          \        /       \         /         \
        O ---------- R ------ R------ R ----- R ----------- T
       / \                   / \             / \           / \
      /  <--S=0--           /   \           /   \         / <--S=0--
     /     \               /     \         /     \       /     \
    R ----- R ----------- R ----- R ----- R ----- R ---- R----- R
                <--S=0--   <--S=0-- <--S=0-- <--S=0--    <--S=0--

    >---- RREQ-Instance (Control: O-->T;  Data: T-->O) ------->
    <---- RREP-Instance (Control: T-->O;  Data: O-->T) -------<]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
	As illustrated in <xref target="figSymm-b"/>, an intermediate
	router determines the S bit value that the RREQ-DIO should carry
	using link asymmetry detection methods as discussed earlier in
	this section.  In many cases, the intermediate router has already
	made the link asymmetry decision by the time RREQ-DIO arrives.
      </t>
      <t>
	See <xref target="Examples"/> for examples illustrating RREQ and RREP
        transmissions in some networks with symmetric and asymmetric links.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="aodvrplop">
      <name>AODV-RPL Operation</name>
      <section anchor="rreq">
        <name>Generating RREQ</name>
        <t>
	The route discovery process is initiated when an application
	at the OrigNode has data to be transmitted to the TargNode but does
	not have a route that satisfies the OF for the target
	of the application's data. In this case, the OrigNode builds a local
	RPL Instance and a DODAG rooted at itself. Then, it transmits a DIO
	message containing exactly one RREQ option
	(see <xref target="RREQmsg"/>) to multicast group all-AODV-RPL-nodes.
	The RREQ-DIO <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain at least one ART option
	(see <xref target="artop"/>), which indicates the TargNode.
	The S bit in RREQ-DIO sent out by the OrigNode is set to 1.
        </t>
        <t>
	Each node maintains a Sequence Number; the operation is specified in
	<xref target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="of" section="7.2"/>.
	When the OrigNode initiates a
	route discovery process, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> increase its own Sequence Number to
	avoid conflicts with previously established routes.  The Sequence
	Number is carried in the Orig SeqNo field of the RREQ option.
        </t>
        <t> The Target Prefix / Address in the ART option can be a unicast IPv6
	address or a prefix.  The OrigNode can initiate
	the route discovery process for multiple targets simultaneously by
	including multiple ART options. Within an RREQ-DIO, the OF for the routes to different TargNodes <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the same.
        </t>
        <t> OrigNode can maintain different RPL Instances to discover routes with
	different requirements to the same targets. Using the RPLInstanceID
	pairing mechanism (see <xref target="instancepairing"/>), route replies
	(RREP-DIOs) for different RPL Instances can be generated.
        </t>
        <t> The transmission of RREQ-DIO obeys the Trickle timer
	<xref target="RFC6206"/>.  If the duration specified by the
	L field has elapsed, the OrigNode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> leave
	the DODAG and stop sending RREQ-DIOs in the related RPL Instance.
	OrigNode needs to set the L field such that the DODAG will not
	prematurely timeout during data transfer with the TargNode.
	For setting this value, it has to consider factors such as
	the Trickle timer, TargNode hop distance, network size, link
	behavior, expected data usage time, and so on.
        </t>
      </section>
    <section anchor="process_rreq">
        <name>Receiving and Forwarding RREQ Messages</name>
        <section anchor="rreq_step1">
          <name>Step 1: RREQ Reception and Evaluation</name>
	  <t>When a router X receives an RREQ message over a link from a
	  neighbor Y, X first determines whether or not the RREQ is valid.  If
	  valid, X then determines whether or not it has sufficient resources
	  available to maintain the RREQ-Instance and the value of the S bit
	  needed to process an eventual RREP, if the RREP were to be received.
	  If not valid, then X <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> either free up sufficient resources (the
	  means for this are beyond the scope of this document), or drop the
	  packet and discontinue processing of the RREQ.  Otherwise, X next
	  determines whether the RREQ advertises a usable route to OrigNode,
	  by checking whether the link to Y can be used to transmit packets to
	  OrigNode.
          </t>
          <t>
	    When H=0 in the incoming RREQ, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> drop the
	    RREQ-DIO if one of its addresses is present in the Address Vector.
	    When H=1 in the incoming RREQ, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> drop the RREQ
	    message if the Orig SeqNo field of the RREQ is older than the SeqNo
	    value that X has stored for a route to OrigNode.
	    Otherwise, the router determines whether to propagate the RREQ-DIO.
	    It does this by determining whether or not a route to OrigNode
	    using the upstream direction of the incoming link satisfies the
	    Objective Function (OF).  In order to evaluate the OF, the router
	    first determines the maximum useful Rank (MaxUsefulRank).  If the
	    router has previously joined the RREQ-Instance associated with
	    the RREQ-DIO, then MaxUsefulRank is set to be the Rank value that
	    was stored when the router processed the best previous RREQ for
	    the DODAG with the given RREQ-Instance.  Otherwise, MaxUsefulRank
	    is set to be RankLimit.  If OF cannot be satisfied (i.e.,
	    the Rank evaluates to a value greater than MaxUsefulRank),
	    the RREQ-DIO <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be dropped, and the following steps are not
	    processed.  Otherwise, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> join the RREQ-Instance
	    and prepare to propagate the RREQ-DIO, as follows. The upstream
	    neighbor router that transmitted the received RREQ-DIO is selected
	    as the preferred parent in the RREQ-Instance.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rreq_step2">
          <name>Step 2: TargNode and Intermediate Router Determination</name>
          <t>
	    After determining that a received RREQ provides a usable route
	    to OrigNode, a router determines whether it is a TargNode, a possible intermediate router between OrigNode and a TargNode,
	    or both.  The router is a TargNode if it finds one of its own
	    addresses in a Target option in the RREQ.  After possibly
	    propagating the RREQ according to the procedures in Steps 3,
	    4, and 5, the TargNode generates an RREP as specified in
	    <xref target="gen-rrep"/>.  If S=0, the determination of TargNode
	    status and determination of a usable route to OrigNode is the same.
          </t>
          <t>
	    If the OrigNode tries to reach multiple TargNodes in a
	    single RREQ-Instance, one of the TargNodes can be an intermediate
	    router to other TargNodes.  In this case, before transmitting the
	    RREQ-DIO to multicast group all-AODV-RPL-nodes, a TargNode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	    delete the Target option encapsulating its own address, so that
	    downstream routers with higher Rank values do not try to create
	    a route to this TargNode.
          </t>
          <t>
	    An intermediate router could receive several RREQ-DIOs from
	    routers with lower Rank values in the same RREQ-Instance with
	    different lists of Target options.  For the purposes of determining
	    the intersection with previous incoming RREQ-DIOs, the intermediate
	    router maintains a record of the targets that have been requested
	    for a given RREQ-Instance.  An incoming RREQ-DIO message having
	    multiple ART options coming from a router with higher Rank than
	    the Rank of the stored targets is ignored.  When transmitting the
	    RREQ-DIO, the intersection of all received lists <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included
	    if it is nonempty after TargNode has deleted the Target option
	    encapsulating its own address.  If the intersection is empty, it
	    means that all the targets have been reached, and the router <bcp14>MUST
	    NOT</bcp14> transmit any RREQ-DIO.  Otherwise, it proceeds to
	    <xref target="rreq_step3"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
	    For example, suppose two RREQ-DIOs are received with the same
	    RPL Instance and OrigNode.  Suppose further that the first
	    RREQ has (T1, T2) as the targets, and the second one has (T2, T4)
	    as targets. Then, only T2 needs to be included in the generated
	    RREQ-DIO.
          </t>
          <t>
	    The reasoning for using the intersection of the lists in the
	    RREQs is as follows.  When two or more RREQs are received with
            the same Orig SeqNo, they were transmitted by OrigNode with the
            same destinations and OF.  When an intermediate node receives two
            RREQs with the same Orig SeqNo but different lists of destinations,
            that means that some intermediate nodes retransmitting the RREQs
            have already deleted themselves from the list of destinations
	    before they retransmitted the RREQ.  Those deleted nodes are
            not to be reinserted back into the list of destinations.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rreq_step3">
          <name>Step 3: Intermediate Router RREQ Processing</name>
          <t>
	    The intermediate router establishes itself as a viable node
	    for a route to OrigNode as follows.  If the H bit is set to 1,
	    for a hop-by-hop route, then the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> build or update
	    its upward route entry towards OrigNode, which includes at least
	    the following items: Source Address, RPLInstanceID, Destination
	    Address, Next Hop, Lifetime, and Sequence Number.
            The Destination Address and the RPLInstanceID can be
	    learned from the DODAGID and the RPLInstanceID of the RREQ-DIO, respectively.
	    The Source Address is the address used by the router to
	    send data to the Next Hop, i.e., the preferred parent.
	    The lifetime is set according to DODAG configuration (not
	    the L field) and can be extended when the route is actually used.
	    The Sequence Number represents the freshness of the route entry;
	    it is copied from the Orig SeqNo field of the RREQ option. A route
	    entry with the same source and destination address and the same
	    RPLInstanceID, but a stale Sequence Number (i.e., incoming Sequence
	    Number is less than the currently stored Sequence Number of the
	    route entry), <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be deleted.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rreq_step4">
          <name>Step 4: Symmetric Route Processing at an Intermediate Router</name>
          <t>
	    If the S bit of the incoming RREQ-DIO is 0, then the route cannot
	    be symmetric, and the S bit of the RREQ-DIO to be transmitted is
	    set to 0.  Otherwise, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> determine
	    whether the downward direction (i.e., towards the TargNode) of the
	    incoming link satisfies the OF.  If it does, the S bit of the
	    RREQ-DIO to be transmitted is set to 1.  Otherwise, the S bit of
	    the RREQ-DIO to be transmitted is set to 0.
          </t>
          <t>
	    When a router joins the RREQ-Instance, it also associates within
	    its data structure for the RREQ-Instance the information about
	    whether or not the RREQ-DIO to be transmitted has the S bit set
	    to 1.  This information
	    associated to RREQ-Instance is known as the S bit of the
	    RREQ-Instance. It will be used later during the RREP-DIO message
	    processing (see <xref target="asymmetricrrep"/>).
          </t>

          <t>Suppose a router has joined the RREQ-Instance, the H bit is set
          to 0, and the S bit of the RREQ-Instance is set to 1.  In this case,
          the router <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> optionally include the Address Vector
          of the symmetric route back to OrigNode as part of the RREQ-Instance
          data.  This is useful if the router later receives an RREP-DIO that
          is paired with the RREQ-Instance.  If the router does NOT include
          the Address Vector, then it has to rely on multicast for the RREP.
          The multicast can impose a substantial performance penalty.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rreq_step5">
          <name>Step 5: RREQ Propagation at an Intermediate Router</name>
          <t>
	    If the router is an intermediate router, then it transmits the
	    RREQ-DIO to the multicast group all-AODV-RPL-nodes; if the H bit is
	    set to 0, the intermediate router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> append
	    the address of its interface receiving the RREQ-DIO into the
	    Address Vector.  In addition, if the address of the router's
	    interface transmitting the RREQ-DIO is not the same as the address
            of the interface receiving the RREQ-DIO, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also
	    append the transmitting interface address into the Address Vector.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rreq_step6">
          <name>Step 6: RREQ Reception at TargNode</name>
          <t>
	    If the router is a TargNode and was already associated with the
	    RREQ-Instance, it takes no further action and does not send an
	    RREP-DIO.  If TargNode is not already associated with the
	    RREQ-Instance, it prepares and transmits an RREP-DIO, possibly
	    after waiting for RREP_WAIT_TIME, as detailed in
	    (<xref target="gen-rrep"/>).
          </t>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="gen-rrep">
        <name>Generating RREP at TargNode</name>
        <t> When a TargNode receives an RREQ message over a link from a
        neighbor Y, TargNode first follows the procedures in <xref
        target="process_rreq"/>.  If the link to Y can be used to transmit
        packets to OrigNode, TargNode generates an RREP according to Sections
        <xref format="counter" target="rrepsymmetric"/> and <xref
        target="asymmetricrrep" format="counter"/>.  Otherwise, TargNode
        drops the RREQ and does not generate an RREP.
        </t>
        <t>
	    If the L field is not 0, the TargNode <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> delay transmitting the
	    RREP-DIO for the duration RREP_WAIT_TIME to await a route with a lower
	    Rank.  The value of RREP_WAIT_TIME is set by default to 1/4 of
	    the duration determined by the L field.  For L == 0,
	    RREP_WAIT_TIME is set by default to 0.  Depending upon the
	    application, RREP_WAIT_TIME may be set to other values.
	    Smaller values enable quicker formation for the P2P route.
	    Larger values enable formation of P2P routes with better
	    Rank values.
        </t>
        <t>
	    The address of the OrigNode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
	    encapsulated in the ART option and included in this RREP-DIO
	    message along with the SeqNo of TargNode.
        </t>
        <section anchor="rrepsymmetric">
          <name>RREP-DIO for Symmetric Route</name>
          <t>
	    If the RREQ-Instance corresponding to the RREQ-DIO that arrived
	    at TargNode has the S bit set to 1, there
	    is a symmetric route, both of whose directions satisfy the
	    OF. Other RREQ-DIOs might later provide better
	    upward routes.  The method of selection between a
	    qualified symmetric route and an asymmetric route that might have
	    better performance is implementation specific and out of scope.
          </t>
	<t>
	    For a symmetric route, the RREP-DIO message is unicast to the Next
	    Hop according to the Address Vector (H=0) or the route
	    entry (H=1);  the DODAG in RREP-Instance does not need to be
	    built.  The RPLInstanceID in the RREP-Instance is paired as
	    defined in <xref target="instancepairing"/>.  If the H bit
	    is set to 0, the Address Vector from the RREQ-DIO <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
	    included in the RREP-DIO.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="asymmetricrrep">
          <name>RREP-DIO for Asymmetric Route</name>
          <t>
	    When an RREQ-DIO arrives at a TargNode with the S bit set to 0,
	    the TargNode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> build a DODAG in the RREP-Instance
	    corresponding to the RREQ-DIO rooted at itself, in order to
	    provide OrigNode with a downstream route
	    to the TargNode. The RREP-DIO message is transmitted to
	    multicast group all-AODV-RPL-nodes.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="instancepairing">
          <name>RPLInstanceID Pairing</name>
          <t>
	  Since the RPLInstanceID is assigned locally (i.e., there is no
	  coordination between routers in the assignment of RPLInstanceID), the
	  tuple (OrigNode, TargNode, RPLInstanceID) is needed to uniquely
	  identify a discovered route. It is possible that multiple route
	  discoveries with dissimilar OFs
	  are initiated simultaneously. Thus, between the same pair of OrigNode
	  and TargNode, there can be multiple AODV-RPL route discovery
	  instances.  So that OrigNode and TargNode can avoid any mismatch,
	  they <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> pair the RREQ-Instance and the RREP-Instance in the same
	  route discovery by using the RPLInstanceID.
          </t>
          <t>
	  When preparing the RREP-DIO, a TargNode could find the RPLInstanceID
	  candidate for the RREP-Instance is already occupied by another RPL
	  Instance from an earlier route discovery operation that is still
	  active.  This unlikely case might happen if two distinct OrigNodes
	  need routes to the same TargNode, and they happen to use the same
	  RPLInstanceID for RREQ-Instance. In such cases, the
	  RPLInstanceID of an already active RREP-Instance <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used
	  again for assigning RPLInstanceID for the later RREP-Instance.
	  If the same RPLInstanceID were reused for two
	  distinct DODAGs originated with the same DODAGID (TargNode address),
	  intermediate routers could not distinguish between these
	  DODAGs (and their associated OFs). Instead, the
	  RPLInstanceID <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be replaced by another value so that the two
	  RREP-Instances can be distinguished.  In the RREP-DIO option, the
	  Delta field of the RREP-DIO message (<xref target="figRREP"/>)
	  indicates the value that TargNode adds to the
	  RPLInstanceID in the RREQ-DIO that it received, to obtain the value
	  of the RPLInstanceID it uses in the RREP-DIO message.
	  0 indicates that the RREQ-InstanceID has the same value as
          the RPLInstanceID of the RREP message.
	  When the new RPLInstanceID after incrementation exceeds 255, it
	  rolls over starting at 0. For example, if the RREQ-InstanceID
	  is 252 and incremented by 6, the new RPLInstanceID will be 2.
	  Related operations can be found in <xref target="forwardRREP"/>.
	  RPLInstanceID collisions do not occur across RREQ-DIOs; the
	  DODAGID equals the OrigNode address and is sufficient to
	  disambiguate between DODAGs.
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="forwardRREP">
        <name>Receiving and Forwarding RREP</name>
        <t> Upon receiving an RREP-DIO, a router that already belongs to the
	    RREP-Instance <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> drop the RREP-DIO.  Otherwise, the router
 	    performs the steps in the following subsections.
        </t>
        <section anchor="rrep_step1">
          <name>Step 1: Receiving and Evaluation</name>
          <t>
	    If the OF is not satisfied, the router <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
	    join the DODAG; the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard the RREP-DIO and does not
	    execute the remaining steps in this section.  An intermediate
	    router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard an RREP if one of its addresses is present
	    in the Address Vector and does not execute the remaining steps in
	    this section.
          </t>
          <t>
	    If the S bit of the associated RREQ-Instance is set to 1,
	    the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> proceed to <xref target="rrep_step2"/>.
          </t>

          <t> If the S bit of the RREQ-Instance is set to 0, the router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          determine whether the downward direction of the link (towards the
          TargNode) over which the RREP-DIO is received satisfies the
          OF and whether the router's Rank would not exceed
          the RankLimit.  If these are true, the router joins the DODAG of the
          RREP-Instance.  The router that transmitted the received RREP-DIO is
          selected as the preferred parent.  Afterwards, other RREP-DIO
          messages can be received; AODV-RPL does not specify any action to be
          taken in such cases.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rrep_step2">
          <name>Step 2: OrigNode or Intermediate Router</name>
          <t>The router updates its stored value of the TargNode's Sequence
	  Number according to the value provided in the ART option.  The router next
	  checks if one of its addresses is included in the ART option.  If it is
	  included, this router is the OrigNode of the route discovery. Otherwise, it is
   an intermediate router.</t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rrep_step3">
          <name>Step 3: Build Route to TargNode</name>
          <t>
	    If the H bit is set to 1, then the router (OrigNode or
	    intermediate) <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> build a downward route entry towards TargNode
	    that includes at least the following items: OrigNode Address,
	    RPLInstanceID, TargNode Address as destination, Next Hop, Lifetime,
	    and Sequence Number.  For a symmetric route, the Next Hop in the
	    route entry is the router from which the RREP-DIO is received.  For
	    an asymmetric route, the Next Hop is the preferred parent in the
	    DODAG of RREP-Instance.  The RPLInstanceID in the route entry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	    be the RREQ-InstanceID (i.e., after subtracting the Delta field
	    value from the value of the RPLInstanceID).  The source address is
	    learned from the ART option, and
	    the destination address is learned from the DODAGID.  The lifetime
	    is set according to DODAG configuration (i.e., not the L field)
	    and can be extended when the route is actually used. The Sequence
	    Number represents the freshness of the route entry and is copied
	    from the Dest SeqNo field of the ART option of the RREP-DIO.
	    A route entry with the same source and destination address and the same
	    RPLInstanceID, but a stale Sequence Number, <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be deleted.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section anchor="rrep_step4">
          <name>Step 4: RREP Propagation</name>
          <t>
	    If the receiver is the OrigNode, it can start transmitting the
	    application data to TargNode along the path as provided in
	    RREP-Instance, and processing for the RREP-DIO is
	    complete. Otherwise, the RREP will be propagated towards OrigNode.
	    If H=0, the intermediate router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the
	    address of the interface receiving the RREP-DIO into the Address
	   Vector.  If H=1, according to the previous step, the intermediate
	    router has set up a route entry for TargNode. If the intermediate
	    router has a route to OrigNode, it uses that route to unicast the
	    RREP-DIO to OrigNode.  Otherwise, in the case of a symmetric route,
	    the RREP-DIO message is unicast to the Next Hop according to the
	    Address Vector in the RREP-DIO (H=0) or the local route entry
	    (H=1).  Otherwise, in the case of an asymmetric route, the
	    intermediate router transmits the RREP-DIO to multicast group
	    all-AODV-RPL-nodes.  The RPLInstanceID in the transmitted RREP-DIO
	    is the same as the value in the received RREP-DIO.
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>

<section anchor="G-RREP">
      <name>Gratuitous RREP</name>
      <t>
	In some cases, an intermediate router that receives an RREQ-DIO message
	<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> unicast a Gratuitous RREP-DIO (G-RREP-DIO) message back to OrigNode before
	continuing the transmission of the RREQ-DIO towards TargNode.  The Gratuitous RREP
	(G-RREP) allows the OrigNode to start transmitting
	data to TargNode sooner.  The G bit of the RREP option is provided to
	distinguish the G-RREP-DIO (G=1) sent by the intermediate
	router from the RREP-DIO sent by TargNode (G=0).
      </t>
      <t>
	The G-RREP-DIO <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be sent out when the intermediate router
	receives an RREQ-DIO for a TargNode and the router has a pair of
	downward and upward routes to the TargNode that also satisfy the
	OF and for which the Destination Sequence Number is
	at least as large as the Sequence Number in the RREQ-DIO message.
	After unicasting the G-RREP to the OrigNode, the intermediate
	router then unicasts the RREQ towards TargNode, so that TargNode will
	have the advertised route towards OrigNode along with the
	RREQ-InstanceID for the RREQ-Instance.  An upstream intermediate
	router that receives such a G-RREP <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> also generate a G-RREP and
        send it further upstream towards OrigNode.
      </t>
      <t>
	In case of source routing, the intermediate router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the
	Address Vector between the OrigNode and itself in the
	G-RREP.  It also includes the Address Vector in the unicast
	RREQ-DIO towards TargNode.  Upon reception of the unicast RREQ-DIO,
	the TargNode will have a
	route Address Vector from itself to the OrigNode. Then, the
	router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the Address Vector from the TargNode to the
	router itself in the G-RREP-DIO to be transmitted.
      </t>
      <t>
	For establishing hop-by-hop routes, the intermediate router <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	unicast the received RREQ-DIO to the Next Hop on the route. The Next
	Hop router along the route <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> build new route entries with the related
	RPLInstanceID and DODAGID in the downward direction. This process
	repeats at each node until the RREQ-DIO arrives at the TargNode.
	Then, the TargNode and each router along the path towards OrigNode
	<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> unicast the RREP-DIO hop-by-hop towards OrigNode
	as specified in <xref target="gen-rrep"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

<section anchor="trickle">
      <name>Operation of Trickle Timer</name>
      <t>
	RREQ-Instance/RREP-Instance multicast uses Trickle timer operations
	<xref target="RFC6206"/> to control RREQ-DIO and
	RREP-DIO transmissions.  The Trickle control of these DIO transmissions
	follows the procedures described in 
	<xref target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="of" section="8.3"/> entitled "DIO Transmission".  If the route is
	symmetric, the RREP-DIO does not need the Trickle timer mechanism.

      </t>
    </section>


<section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <t>
AODV-RPL uses the "P2P Route Discovery Mode of Operation" (MOP == 4), with new
options as specified in this document. This document has been added as an
additional reference for "P2P Route Discovery Mode of Operation" in the "Mode
of Operation" registry within the "Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy
Networks (RPL)" registry group.
      </t>
      <t>
	IANA has assigned the three new AODV-RPL options described in <xref
	target="ianaOpts"/> in the "RPL Control Message Options" registry
	within the "Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy Networks (RPL)"
	registry group.
      </t>
      <table anchor="ianaOpts">
        <name>AODV-RPL Options</name>
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Value</th>
	    <th>Meaning</th>
            <th>Reference</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td>0x0B</td>
	    <td>RREQ</td>
	    <td>RFC 9854</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>0x0C</td>
	    <td>RREP</td>
	    <td>RFC 9854</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td>0x0D</td>
	    <td>ART</td>
	    <td>RFC 9854</td>
	  </tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <t> 
        IANA has allocated the permanent multicast address with
        link-local scope in <xref target="ianaMultiAddress"/> for nodes implementing
        this specification. This allocation has been made in the "Local Network Control Block
        (224.0.0.0 - 224.0.0.255 (224.0.0/24))" registry within the
        "IPv4 Multicast Address Space Registry" registry group.
      </t>

<table anchor="ianaMultiAddress">
  <name>Permanent Multicast Address with Link-Local Scope</name>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Address(es)</th>
      <th>Description</th>
      <th>References</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>224.0.0.69</td>
      <td>all-AODV-RPL-nodes</td>
      <td>RFC 9854</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
      
    </section>

<section anchor="sec">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>The security considerations for the operation of AODV-RPL are similar
      to those for the operation of RPL (as described in Section <xref
      target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="bare" section="19"/> of the RPL
      specification <xref target="RFC6550"/>).  Sections <xref
      target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="bare" section="6.1"/> and <xref
      target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="bare" section="10"/> of <xref
      target="RFC6550"/> describe RPL's optional security framework, which
      AODV-RPL relies on to provide data confidentiality, authentication,
      replay protection, and delay protection services.  Additional analysis
      for the security threats to RPL can be found in <xref
      target="RFC7416"/>.</t>
      <t>A router can join a temporary DAG created for a secure AODV-RPL route
      discovery only if it can support the security configuration in use (see
      <xref target="RFC6550" sectionFormat="of" section="6.1"/>), which also
      specifies the key in use.  It does not matter whether the key is
      preinstalled or dynamically acquired.  The router must have the key in
      use before it can join the DAG being created for secure route
      discovery.</t>

      <t>If a rogue router knows the key for the security configuration in
      use, it can join the secure AODV-RPL route discovery and cause various
      types of damage.  Such a rogue router could advertise false information
      in its DIOs in order to include itself in the discovered route(s).  It
      could generate bogus RREQ-DIO and RREP-DIO messages carrying bad
      routes or maliciously modify genuine RREP-DIO messages it receives.  A
      rogue router acting as the OrigNode could launch denial-of-service
      attacks against the LLN deployment by initiating fake AODV-RPL route
      discoveries.  When rogue routers might be present, RPL's preinstalled
      mode of operation, where the key to use for route discovery is
      preinstalled, <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be used.
      </t>
      <t>
    When an RREQ-DIO message uses the source routing option by setting the H
    bit to 0, a rogue router may populate the Address Vector field with a set
    of addresses that may result in the RREP-DIO traveling in a routing loop.
      </t>
      <t>
	If a rogue router is able to forge a G-RREP,
	it could mount denial-of-service attacks.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>

<references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6206.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6550.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6551.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3561.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6687.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6997.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6998.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7416.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7548.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7276.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9010.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9030.xml"/>

<reference anchor="co-ioam" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8328276">
          <front>
            <title>
                Co-iOAM: In-situ Telemetry Metadata Transport for
                Resource Constrained Networks within IETF Standards Framework
            </title>
            <author fullname="Rashmi Ballamajalu" initials="R." surname="Ballamajalu">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="S.V.R. Anand" initials="S.V.R." surname="Anand">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Malati Hegde" initials="M." surname="Hegde">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <date month="Jan" year="2018"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>2018 10th International Conference on Communication Systems &amp; Networks (COMSNETS), pp. 573-576</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/COMSNETS.2018.8328276"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="aodv-tot" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/749281">
          <front>
            <title>
                Ad-hoc On-demand Distance Vector Routing
            </title>
            <author fullname="C.E. Perkins" initials="C.E." surname="Perkins">
              <organization>Advanced Development Group, Sun MicroSystems
              Laboratories, Inc., Menlo Park, CA, USA</organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="E.M. Royer" initials="E.M." surname="Royer">
              <organization>Advanced Development Group, Sun MicroSystems
              Laboratories, Inc., Menlo Park, CA, USA</organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <date month="Feb" year="1999"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Proceedings WMCSA'99. Second IEEE Workshop on Mobile Computing Systems and Applications, pp. 90-100</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/MCSA.1999.749281"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="cooja" target="https://github.com/contiki-os/contiki/tree/master/tools/cooja">
          <front>
            <title> Cooja Simulator for Wireless Sensor Networks
                   (Contiki/Cooja Version 2.7)
            </title>
            <author/>
            <date month="Nov" year="2013"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>commit 7635906</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="contiki" target="https://github.com/contiki-os/contiki">
          <front>
            <title> The Contiki Open Source OS for the Internet of Things
                    (Contiki Version 2.7)
            </title>
            <author/>
            <date month="Nov" year="2013"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>commit 7635906</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Contiki-ng" target="https://github.com/contiki-ng/contiki-ng">
          <front>
            <title> Contiki-NG: The OS for Next Generation IoT Devices
                    (Contiki-NG Version 4.6)
            </title>
            <author/>
            <date month="Dec" year="2020"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>commit 3b0bc6a</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Link_Asymmetry" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/1689239.1689242">
          <front>
            <title>
		On Link Asymmetry and One-way Estimation in Wireless
		Sensor Networks
            </title>
            <author fullname="Lifeng Sang" initials="L." surname="Sang">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Anish Arora" initials="A." surname="Arora">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Hongwei Zhang" initials="H." surname="Zhang">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2010"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>ACM Transactions on Sensor Networks, vol. 6, no. 2, pp. 1-25</refcontent>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/1689239.1689242"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="low-power-wireless" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/1689239.1689246">
          <front>
            <title>
		An empirical study of low-power wireless
            </title>
            <author fullname="Kannan Srinivasan" initials="K." surname="Srinivasan">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Prabal Dutta" initials="P." surname="Dutta">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Arsalan Tavakoli" initials="A." surname="Tavakoli">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Philip Levis" initials="P" surname="Levis">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2010"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>ACM Transactions on Sensor Networks, vol. 6, no. 2, pp. 1-49</refcontent>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1145/1689239.1689246"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="empirical-study" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6231290">
          <front>
            <title>
		An empirical study of asymmetry in low-power wireless links
            </title>
            <author fullname="Prasant Misra" initials="P." surname="Misra">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Nadeem Ahmed" initials="N." surname="Ahmed">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Sanjay Jha" initials="S." surname="Jha">
              <organization> </organization>
              <address>
            </address>
            </author>
            <date month="July" year="2012"/>
          </front>
          <refcontent>IEEE Communications Magazine, vol. 50, no. 7, pp. 137-146</refcontent>
	  <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/MCOM.2012.6231290"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="appendix-a">
      <name>Example: Using ETX/RSSI Values to Determine Value of S Bit</name>
      <t>The combination of the downstream Received Signal Strength Indicator
      (RSSI) and the upstream Expected Transmission Count (ETX) has been
      tested to determine whether a link is symmetric or asymmetric at
      intermediate routers. We present two methods to obtain an ETX value from
      RSSI measurement.</t>

      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>Method 1:</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
	    In the first method, we constructed a table measuring RSSI versus
	    ETX using the Cooja simulation <xref target="cooja"/> setup in the
	    Contiki OS environment <xref target="contiki"/>. We used
	    Contiki-2.7 running the 6LoWPAN/RPL protocol stack for the
	    simulations.  For approximating the number of packet drops based
	    on the RSSI values, we implemented simple logic that drops
	    transmitted packets with certain predefined ratios before handing
	    over the packets to the receiver. The packet drop ratio is
	    implemented as a table lookup of RSSI ranges mapping to different
	    packet drop ratios with lower RSSI ranges resulting in higher
	    values. While this table has been defined for the purpose of
	    capturing the overall link behavior, in general, it is highly
	    recommended to conduct physical radio measurement experiments.  By
	    keeping the receiving node at different distances, we let the
	    packets experience different packet drops as per the described
	    method. The ETX value computation is done by another module that
	    is part of RPL OF implementation.  Since the ETX
	    value is reflective of the extent of packet drops, it allowed us
	    to prepare a useful table correlating ETX and RSSI values (see
	    <xref target="table_ETX_RSSI"/>).  ETX and RSSI values obtained in this way may be used as
	    explained below:</t>

          <figure anchor="commlink">
            <name>Communication Link from Source to Destination</name>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Source -------> NodeA -------> NodeB -----> Destination]]></artwork>
          </figure>

      <table anchor="table_ETX_RSSI">
        <name>Selection of S Bit Based on Expected ETX Value</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center">RSSI at NodeA for NodeB</th>
            <th align="center">Expected ETX at NodeA for NodeB-&gt;NodeA</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">&gt; -60</td>
            <td align="center">150</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">-70 to -60</td>
            <td align="center">192</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">-80 to -70</td>
            <td align="center">226</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">-90 to -80</td>
            <td align="center">662</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">-100 to -90</td>
            <td align="center">3840</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      </dd>

        <dt>Method 2:</dt>
        <dd>One could also make use of the function
	    guess_etx_from_rssi() defined in the 6LoWPAN/RPL protocol stack
            of Contiki-ng OS <xref target="Contiki-ng"/> to obtain RSSI-ETX
	    mapping. This function outputs an ETX value ranging between 128
	    and 3840 for -60 &lt;= rssi &lt;= -89. The function description
	    is beyond the scope of this document.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <t> We tested the operations in this specification by making the
      following experiment, using the above parameters.  In our experiment, a
      communication link is considered as symmetric if the ETX value of
      NodeA-&gt;NodeB and NodeB-&gt;NodeA (see <xref target="commlink"/>) are
      within, say, a 1:3 ratio.  This ratio should be understood as
      determining the link's symmetric/asymmetric nature.  NodeA can typically
      know the ETX value in the direction of NodeA-&gt;NodeB, but it has no
      direct way of knowing the value of ETX from NodeB-&gt;NodeA.  Using
      physical testbed experiments and realistic wireless channel propagation
      models, one can determine a relationship between RSSI and ETX
      representable as an expression or a mapping table.  Such a relationship,
      in turn, can be used to estimate the ETX value at NodeA for link
      NodeB-&gt;NodeA from the received RSSI from NodeB.  Whenever NodeA
      determines that the link towards the NodeB is bidirectional asymmetric,
      then the S bit is set to 0.  Afterwards, the link from NodeA to
      Destination remains designated as asymmetric, and the S bit remains set
      to 0.
      </t>
      <t>Determination of asymmetry versus bidirectionality remains a topic
	of lively discussion in the IETF.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Examples">
      <name>Some Example AODV-RPL Message Flows</name>
      <t>
	This appendix provides some example message flows showing
        RREQ and RREP establishing symmetric and asymmetric routes.
	Also, examples for the use of RREP_WAIT and G-RREP are included.
        In the examples, router (O) is to be understood as performing
        the role of OrigNode.  Router (T) is to be understood as performing
	the role of TargNode.  Routers (R) are intermediate routers that
        are performing AODV-RPL functions in order to discover one or more
        suitable routes between (O) and (T).
      </t>
      <section anchor="Asymmetric-examples">
        <name>Example Control Message Flows in Symmetric and Asymmetric Networks</name>
        <t>
	In the following diagram, RREQ messages are multicast from router (O)
	in order to discover routes to and from router (T).  The RREQ control
        messages flow outward from (O).  Each router along the way establishes
        a single RREQ-Instance identified by RREQ-InstanceID even if multiple
        RREQs are received with the same RREQ-InstanceID.  In the top half of
        the diagram, the routers are able to offer a symmetric route at each
        hop of the path from (O) to (T).  When (T) receives an RREQ, it is
        then able to transmit data packets to (O).  Router (T) then prepares
        to send an RREP along the symmetric path that would enable router (O)
        to send packets to router (T).

        </t>
        <figure anchor="figSymm-RREQ_flow">
          <name>AODV-RPL RREQ Message Flow Example When Symmetric Path Available</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
             (R) ---RREQ(S=1)--->(R) ---RREQ(S=1)--->(R)
              ^                                       |
              |                                       |
         RREQ(S=1)                                RREQ(S=1)
              |                                       |
              |                                       v
             (O) --------->(R) --------->(R)-------->(T)
             / \    RREQ         RREQ         RREQ    ^
             |  \    (S=1)      (S=0)         (S=0)   |
             |   \                                   /
        RREQ |    \ RREQ (S=1)                    RREQ (S=0)
       (S=0) |     \                               /
             v      \              RREQ (S=0)     /
            (R) ---->(R)------>(R)----.....--->(R)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
	In the following diagram, which results from the above RREQ message
        transmission, a symmetric route is available from (T) to router (O)
        via the routers in the top half of the diagram.  RREP messages are
        sent via unicast along the symmetric route.  Since the RREP message
        is transmitted via unicast, no RREP messages are sent by router (T)
        to the routers in the bottom half of the diagram.

        </t>
        <figure anchor="figSymm-RREP_flow">
          <name>AODV-RPL RREP Message Flow Example When Symmetric Path Available</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
             (R)<------RREP----- (R)<------RREP----- (R)
              |                                       ^
              |                                       |
             RREP                                    RREP
              |                                       |
              v                                       |
             (O) ----------(R) ----------(R) --------(T)
             / \                                      |
             |  \                                     |
             |   \     (no RREP messages sent)       /
             |    \                                 /
             |     \                               /
             |      \                             /
            (R) -----(R)-------(R)----.....----(R)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
	In the following diagram, RREQ messages are multicast from router (O)
        in order to discover routes to and from router (T) as before. As shown,
        no symmetric route is available from (O) to (T).

        </t>
        <figure anchor="figAsymm-RREQ_flow">
          <name>AODV-RPL RREQ Message Flow When Symmetric Path Unavailable</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
             (R) ---RREQ(S=0)--->(R) ---RREQ(S=0)--->(R)
              ^                                       |
              |                                       |
          RREQ(S=1)                                RREQ(S=0)
              |                                       |
              |                                       v
             (O) --------->(R) --------->(R)-------->(T)
             ^ \    RREQ         RREQ      RREQ      |  \
             |  \    (S=1)        (S=0)       (S=0)  |   |
             |   \                                   /   |
             |  RREQ (S=1)              RREQ (S=0)  /   (R)
             |     \                               /     |
             |      \               RREQ (S=0)    /     /
            (R) ---->(R)------>(R)----.....----->(R)---]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
	Upon receiving the RREQ in <xref target="figAsymm-RREQ_flow"/>,
	router (T) then prepares to send an RREP that would enable router (O)
        to send packets to router (T). In <xref target="figAsymm-RREQ_flow"/>,
	since no symmetric route is available from (T) to router (O),
        RREP messages are sent via multicast to all neighboring routers.

        </t>
        <figure anchor="figAsymm-RREP_flow">
          <name>AODV-RPL RREQ and RREP-Instances for Asymmetric Links</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
             (R)<------RREP----- (R)<------RREP----- (R)
              |                                       |
              |                                       |
             RREP                                    RREP
              |                                       |
              |                                       |
              v                                       v
             (O)<--------- (R)<--------- (R)<------- (T)
             ^ \    RREP         RREP        RREP    |  \
             |  \                                    |   |RREP
             |   \                                   /   |
       RREP  |    \ RREP                  RREP      /   (R)
             |     \                               /     |
             |      \                             /     /
           (R)<----- (R)<----- (R)<---.....---- (R)< - RREP
                RREP       RREP         RREP]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

  <section anchor="RREP_WAIT-example">
        <name>Example RREP_WAIT Handling</name>
        <t>
        In <xref target="fig-RREP_WAIT-a"/>, the first RREQ arrives at (T).
        This triggers TargNode to start the RREP_WAIT_TIME timer.

        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig-RREP_WAIT-a">
          <name>TargNode Starts RREP_WAIT</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        (O) --------->(R) --------->(R)-------->(T)
                RREQ         RREQ         RREQ
               (S=1)        (S=0)        (S=0)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>

        In <xref target="fig-RREP_WAIT-b"/>, another RREQ arrives
        before the RREP_WAIT_TIME timer is expired.  It could be preferable
        compared the previously received RREP that caused the
        RREP_WAIT_TIME timer to be set.

        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig-RREP_WAIT-b">
          <name>Waiting TargNode Receives Preferable RREQ</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        (O)                                     (T)
        / \                                      ^
        |  \                                     |
        |   \                                   /
   RREQ |    \ RREQ (S=1)                    RREQ (S=0)
  (S=0) |     \                               /
        v      \              RREQ (S=0)     /
       (R) ---->(R)------>(R)----.....--->(R)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>

        In <xref target="fig-RREP_WAIT-c"/>, the RREP_WAIT_TIME timer
        expires. TargNode selects the path with S=1.

        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig-RREP_WAIT-c">
          <name>RREP_WAIT Expires at TargNode</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        (R) ---RREQ(S=1)--->(R) ---RREQ(S=1)--->(R)
         ^                                       |
         |                                       |
    RREQ(S=1)                                RREQ(S=1)
         |                                       |
         |                                       v
        (O)                                     (T)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

  <section anchor="G-RREP-example">
        <name>Example G-RREP Handling</name>

        <t>In <xref target="fig-G-RREP-a"/>, R* has upward and downward routes
        to TargNode (T) that satisfy the OF of the RPL Instance originated
        by OrigNode (O), and the Destination Sequence Number is at least as large
        as the Sequence Number in the RREQ message.</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-G-RREP-a">
          <name>RREP Triggers G-RREP at Intermediate Node</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        (R) ---RREQ(S=1)--->(R) ---RREQ(S=0)--->(R)
         ^                                       |
         |                                       |
    RREQ(S=1)                                RREQ(S=0)
         |                                       |
         |                                       v
        (O) --------->(R) --------->(R)-------->(T)
        / \    RREQ         RREQ         RREQ    ^
        |  \    (S=1)      (S=0)         (S=0)   |
        |   \                                   /
   RREQ |    \ RREQ (S=1)                      /
  (S=0) |     \                               /
        v      \                             v
       (R) ---->(R*)<------>(R)<----....--->(R)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        In <xref target="fig-G-RREP-b"/>, R* transmits the G-RREP-DIO
        back to OrigNode (O) and forwards the incoming RREQ towards (T).

        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig-G-RREP-b">
          <name>Intermediate Node Initiates G-RREP</name>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        (O)                                     (T)
          \                                      ^
           \                                     |
            \                            (RREQ) /
             \ G-RREP-DIO                      /
              \                               /
               \   (RREQ)       (RREQ)       /
               (R*)------>(R)----....--->(R)]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section numbered="false">

      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors thank <contact fullname="Pascal Thubert"/>, <contact
      fullname="Rahul Jadhav"/>, and <contact fullname="Lijo Thomas"/> for
      their support and valuable input.  The authors specially thank <contact
      fullname="Lavanya H.M."/> for implementing AODV-RPL in Contiki and
      conducting extensive simulation studies.</t>
      <t> The authors would like to acknowledge the reviews, feedback, and
      comments from the following people, in alphabetical order: <contact
      fullname="Roman Danyliw"/>, <contact fullname="Lars Eggert"/>, <contact
      fullname="Benjamin Kaduk"/>, <contact fullname="Tero Kivinen"/>,
      <contact fullname="Erik Kline"/>, <contact fullname="Murray
      Kucherawy"/>, <contact fullname="Warren Kumari"/>, <contact
      fullname="Francesca Palombini"/>, <contact fullname="Alvaro Retana"/>,
      <contact fullname="Ines Robles"/>, <contact fullname="John Scudder"/>,
      <contact fullname="Meral Shirazipour"/>, <contact fullname="Peter Van
      der Stok"/>, <contact fullname="ric Vyncke"/>, and <contact
      fullname="Robert Wilton"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section numbered="false">
      <name>Contributors</name>

    <contact fullname="Abdur Rashid Sangi">
      <organization>Wenzhou-Kean University</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
<postalLine>88 Daxue Rd, Ouhai</postalLine>
<postalLine>Wenzhou</postalLine>
<postalLine>Zhejiang Province, 325060</postalLine>
<postalLine>China</postalLine>
<postalLine>Kean University</postalLine>
<postalLine>1000 Morris Avenue</postalLine>
<postalLine>Union, New Jersey 07083</postalLine>
<postalLine>United States of America</postalLine>
	</postal>
        <email>sangi_bahrian@yahoo.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>



    <contact fullname="Malati Hegde">
      <organization>Indian Institute of Science</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <city>Bangalore</city><code>560012</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>malati@iisc.ac.in</email>
      </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Mingui Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <street>No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>
	  <cityarea>Haidian District</cityarea>
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100095</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zhangmingui@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </contact>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
